<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Israels condition and cause pleaded; or some arguments for the Jews admission into England. Objections answered, cautions added, with a vindication of Mr. Peters from those foul and unjust aspersions cast upon him by W. Prynn, Esq;.</title>
            <author>D. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1677_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202696</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862892</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1677[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Israels condition and cause pleaded; or some arguments for the Jews admission into England. Objections answered, cautions added, with a vindication of Mr. Peters from those foul and unjust aspersions cast upon him by W. Prynn, Esq;.</title>
                  <author>D. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by P.W. for William Larnar and Jonathan Ball at the Black Moor.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: D.L.</note>
                  <note>In part of defense of "Good work for a good magistrate" by Hugh Peters against "The second part of A short demurrer to the Jewes long discontinued remitter into England" by William Prynne.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peters, Hugh, 1598-1660. --  Good work for a good magistrate --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Short demurrer to the Jewes long discontinued remitter into England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jews --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ISRAELS Condition and Cauſe pleaded; Or ſome Arguments for the <hi>JEWS</hi> Admiſsion into <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For my Brethren and Companions ſake I will ſeek to do thee good, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 127.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Brethren, my hearts deſire for <hi>Iſrael</hi> is, that they may be ſaved, <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Objections</hi> anſwered, <hi>Cautions</hi> added, with a <hi>Vindication</hi> of Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> from thoſe foul and unjuſt Aſperſions caſt upon him by <hi>W. Prynn,</hi> Eſq;.</p>
            <q>He that privily ſlandereth his Neigbour will I destroy, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 102.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>P. W.</hi> for <hi>William Larnar</hi> and <hi>Jonathan Ball</hi> at the <hi>Black Moor.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115072:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115072:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>GOd by the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78. concerning the People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he would have deſtroyed them, <hi>had not</hi> Moſes <hi>his Choſen ſtood in the Gap to turn away his wrathfull indignation.</hi> Meek <hi>Moſes</hi> was both in his Perſon and Prayer powerfull with God for their ſafety, and God approved of his Interceſſion and Supplication; and though God told <hi>Moſes</hi> that he would make of him a great Nation, yet <hi>Moſes</hi>'s affection was ſo fix'd on this Peoples preſervation, that he falls earneſtly to pray for them, They are thy People, and what will the Nations ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O the worth of a ſanctified affection! But <hi>Moſes</hi> who was faithfull in all his houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:115072:3"/>who as a Servant is now inveſted in glory; <hi>Abraham</hi> is dead, and the Prophets are dead, and where ſhall we finde any charitable <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> alive who intercedes and acts for this Peoples Converſion or Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</p>
            <p>Some indeed do it, but reſtrictive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conditionally, and ſparingly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting them in their Prayer, as it were by way of <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding them their companies and Congregations, they ſeem to wiſh them ſome good; but they plainly manifeſt it that they would not have them enjoy it, or not amongſt us; at the ſame time expreſſing ſome charity in words, but denying it in deeds.</p>
            <p>What a laudable act is already doe to further this their Admiſſion by Mr. <hi>Coyſh</hi> in providing a perpetual Stipend to Preachers for this end by that weekly Lecture at <hi>Gregories</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:115072:3"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> of fifty pounds <hi>per annum</hi> is known; the Act was noble, and the end univerſally charitable, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he is gloriouſly rewarded, and if we may ſpeak home, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done by a Prophetick Spirit as providing for them (againſt their coming in) a place to hear the power of the Doctrine of <hi>Christ</hi> publickly preached; God certainly gave him ſome knowledg of what ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards come to paſs.</p>
            <p>Which Act of his as it will for ever ſpeak his Charity and Zeal to this People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo it cannot but be thought his Intentions and Hopes were that they ſhould be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers and Hearers of the Word in this place.</p>
            <p>Yet it ſeems a Paradox to preach for it, and receive Rewards for their Labours, if yet they never intend to intreat the <hi>Iews</hi> to hear their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor to be admitted to Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:115072:4"/>in that Congregation, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet up, and allowed preciſely for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Truly I honour the Labourers, and would much more, if they would ſtir up their Auditours to be charitable and harborous to the <hi>Iews,</hi> and that they would ſquare their Doctrines and Uſes to thoſe Ends for which the Lecture is ſet up, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Calling and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of that People.</p>
            <p>For our Good and theirs is this Subject preſented to the World, to inform our judgments, to remove all ill conceits that are lodg'd in ſome mens breaſts againſt their Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſtir up their Zeal and Charity towards them, that if by any means they may provoke them to Repentance and Faith in the Lord JESUS, that ſo both <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> may be all united in the ſame Spirit, and the ſame Faith, to our myſtical Head.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115072:4"/>
            <p>For their Good alſo, that they may be brought out of Darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Light, that they may know the Scriptures and the power of God, and JESUS CHRIST <hi>whom he hath ſent,</hi> that the Veil may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from their Eys and Hearts, that they may know what is the <hi>heighth,</hi> the <hi>length, breadth,</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> of the knowledge of the Lord JESUS CHRIST, that ſo we who were once not the People of God, and they who once were the Beloved of God may come, we to our fulneſs, and they to their ingrafting in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>To conclude, ſince it is not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but certain, that they ſhall be ingrafted, and to all probability the time is almoſt approached, and the fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is almoſt compleated, and that CHRIST is gathering his Saints together from the four Windes under Heaven, and
<pb facs="tcp:115072:5"/>that the Nations are even ripe for the Harveſt, Let not <hi>England</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude or debar their Brethren from enjoying thoſe plentifull means of obtaining Grace and Favour, which by the Goſpel preached are here to be had, to the Glory of our Nation, to the Comfort and Salvation both of our own and their Souls. So ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſcharged my Conſcience in this Work, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yorrs,</hi> D. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115072:5"/>
            <head>ARGUMENTS FOR THE Iews admiſsion INTO ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He long, heavy, and ſad puniſhment inflicted on this dejected, deſpiſed, and diſperſed people, hath various and ſtrong impreſſions upon mens ſpirits; ſome ſcorning any ſociety with them, others hating their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115072:6"/>very name, and perſons, and ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionating their deſpicable condition: hence ſome Countries baniſh and expell them, others do miſerably and cruelly oppreſs and injure them by baſe and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil words and actions; a third ſort do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them their prayers, and expect their calling, and yet will not yield them place or habitation amongſt them; we have ſome in this Nation, who are ſo bitter againſt that poor people, that they have vented their unſatiable ſpleen and malice by their pens, and rather then their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet paſſions ſhould not take place, and work others againſt them, have raked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all the rabble of Popiſh Authors, and filled mens brains with ſtrange ſtories, and their late printed books with margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall notes of Fryars, and Monkes, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots relations, to render that Antient and Honourable Nation of the Jews, odious and deteſtable.</p>
            <p>And 'tis to be wondred at that men who profeſs themſelves ſuch adverſaries to all Popery and Popiſh ſuperſtitions ſhould yet ſearch all the withered and Moth-eaten writers of that Romiſh faction, and fight only with Popiſh weapons againſt the Jews, but the men are ſufficiently known
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115072:6"/>for their language and paſſion, and ſo at preſent we paſs by them, though we ſhall examine and convince them afterwards.</p>
            <p>Therefore as not approving either the malice of the one, or the cruelty of the other, being this peoples Enemies, both being irrationall, uncivil, and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and being of thoſe who pitty and compaſſionate their affliction; for if ever a Nation may truely take up <hi>Iobs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, certainly 'tis this of the Iews, <hi>Pity me, oh pity me, ye my friends, for the hand of the Lord hath touched me;</hi> and though 'tis true that all affliction is juſtly inflicted, where ſin proceeds, provokes, and procures the Puniſhment, and that this people are deep in accounts, yet there is no bar in Gods Word to hinder a tender compaſſion, and Chriſtian love to be ſhewed towards them, much leſs is there any Rule to hate them, oppreſs them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them our Countrie, or our Commerce; neither hath God, our Father and theirs, our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, our, and their precious Redeemer, nor the Holy Ghoſt, the ſpirit of love and truth, nor yet the word of God in any one plain text, line, or expreſſion, in any part of it, none of theſe (we ſay, and that juſtly and truly)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115072:7"/>hath allowed us to rail at them, or revile them with approbrious, and unſavory, and unchriſtian language, much leſs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them all, even civil ſocieties; for though God in his juſtice did threaten to ſcatter them into all Nations, yet he doth not ſay they ſhall be caſt out of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, an have no being amongſt men; and to ſpeak truth, they are to be ſcattered amongſt all people, for if they ſhould not be amongſt all Nations, how ſhould God (and he intends it) gather them out of all Nations? a generall collection implies a generall caſting, and if ſo, why not ſome into <hi>England,</hi> as well as other Countries? why we leſs charitable then all, or moſt of other Nations? we have the word of God powerfully preached amongſt us, and therein we are commanded, <hi>not to vex the ſtranger, to be barborous to ſtrangers, not to hide our ſelves from our own fleſh;</hi> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we cannot but remember the heavy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence denounced by our Saviour againſt ſuch as did denie to entertain ſtrangers, <hi>I was</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>a ſtranger, and ye took me not IN;</hi> therefore, go ye curſed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons inducing this treatiſe, are not popular applauſe, or gains; but firſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115072:7"/>to do ſervice to God and the Church, to ſtop the mouths and pens of the gain-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to ſatisfie the ſcrupulous, and to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon, in the behalf of that Nation, it being lately controverted, but by none yet clearly decided, concerning this peoples admiſſion into <hi>England;</hi> three things for this purpoſe are inſiſted on, and handled.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seven Reaſons and Arguments poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for the Jews admiſsion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Anſwers to the ſeeming objections againſt their coming IN.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A ſhort and ſuccinct Apology or defence of <hi>H. P.</hi> againſt the tedious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and unreaſonable, unconſcionable, and uncharitable ſlander, and reviling of a pragmatical Lawyer, whoſe tongue and pen are againſt every one, Princes, Prieſts, Magiſtrates, Souldiers not excepted, <hi>ex pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Herculem,</hi> you may know the man by his <hi>Roſemary and Bayes,</hi> and by his <hi>flower on the wall;</hi> but to let him alone to be brougt in the Reer, we come to our main intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Jews admiſſion into <hi>England,</hi> and that firſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115072:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt of theſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard, the ſecond of theſe they never had, the third of theſe they never found.</note>1. In hopes of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and that in three reſpects; firſt, by the power and purity of preaching; ſecondly, by our upright dealing in Contracts and Bargains with them; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by our civil and gentle comportment, and love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in our markets and meetings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Arg. Hopes of their converſion. 'Twas the ſaying of our Saviour to Saint <hi>Peter, when thou art converted, convert thy Brethren:</hi> which how effectually he performed, is plainly to be ſeen in that of the <hi>Acts</hi> c. 2. where he did not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, but alſo convert 3000. ſouls at one Sermon. Converſion of a ſinner to God, as it is the greateſt happineſs of him, ſo it hath as large a reward tyed to it; ſuch <hi>ſhall ſhine, ſayes Daniel,</hi> c. 12. <hi>as the ſtars in the firmament,</hi> ſhal cover (ſayes <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſins,</hi> ſhall ſave himſelf &amp; others too, (ſayes the Apoſtle, St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>David</hi> makes it an Augmentation of Gods glory, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115072:8"/>ſinners ſhall be converted to thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. our Saviour ſayes, (there is joy in heaven, over one ſinner that repenteth, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Now as it is, the greateſt happineſs to effect it, and as it is ſo well rewarded, ſo certainly ſhould all indeavour it. 1. To himſelf. 2. To others; and though it hath been ſomtimes immediately wrought by God, and his holy ſpirit, by ſignes and wonders, yet who will deny but that Gods word, powerfully and purely preached, is the uſuall and ordinary way and means to beget faith, and to work repentance unto ſalvation, now to ſpeak truth, In moſt, if not in all parts where the Iews reſide, the Kings, and Princes, and People, are either without Gods word, or elſe uſe not to have it preach'd purely, purely I ſay, for firſt, the <hi>Turks, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> have it not; then ſecondly, other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are wholly Popiſh and ſuperſtitious, their Churches, and houſes, and high-waies ſtored with Images, Crucifixes, of all ſorts and ſizes, all which, the Iews abhorre; and tis feared that the Papiſts doctrine and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline is ſo full of ſcandall and offence to the Jews, that thereby they have forborn to embrace the Goſpel, which as uſed in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115072:9"/>Countries full of Popery, ſeems ſo full of Idolatry, forbidden in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſo have to this day rendred the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel as the ſavour of death, which otherwiſe might have been the ſavour of life unto them, and as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies to the Greeks, it ſeems <hi>fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and to the Iews a <hi>ſtumbling block, and a rock of offence,</hi> ſo that through thoſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh traditions, and ſuperſtitions, and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, <hi>the Word of God is made of none effect;</hi> and therefore as 'tis wondred at, that ſo few Jews in ſo man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Countries, and in ſo many years, have been Converted to Chriſtianity, 'tis plainly known, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are where the Word of God is not preached as it ought to be. A heavy burden for ſuch as ſtand guilty hereof, the more is the pity, the Pope, and King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſtand deep in this particular.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeake home to the purpoſe, what was <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> many years ago, and till of late, but Dens, and Cages of unclean Birds, of <hi>Romes</hi> hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and breeding? were not our Kings and Rulers, Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops, and all the Clergie, Nobility, and Commons bred up in Popery? were not our Temples,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115072:9"/>and Cloiſters, and Houſes, and Cities, and High-waies ſtuffed with Saints, and Saints Relicks, with Croſſe of ſilver and gold, the work of mens hands? and what marvell was it if the <hi>Iews,</hi> who then lived amongſt us, were unconverted, and ſo were hated by the blin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſuperſtitious Clergie, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and obdurate? VVhat hopes were then to ſee the <hi>Iews</hi> converte, when the very teachers and guides of the people were ſo blind that true, and pure, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Religion (as St. <hi>Iames</hi> cals it) was almoſt loſt and gone? One <hi>Wickliff</hi> in one age, one <hi>Tindall</hi> in another, in all <hi>England</hi> a <hi>John Hus,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> in all <hi>Germany,</hi> and after them a <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi> a <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> with ſome few others, in all <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and theſe in their ſeverall generations by the Popiſh Clerg, hated, perſecuted, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and butchered: In <hi>Henry</hi> the Eights reign, but one <hi>Omen;</hi> what ſhould after be accompliſhed by that name, <hi>One Lord Cromwell,</hi> who indeavoured, and did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennel, and diſpoſſeſſe divers of lazie, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and ſcandalous Monks, and Fryars, and Nunnes; and was this a time to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the converſion of the <hi>Jews?</hi> or were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115072:10"/>theſe fat Buls of <hi>Baſan</hi> fit to manage the work of the Goſpel, for the converſion of a people, nor was it their intent to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it in this people, whom they ſo hated.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Quis talia fando,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Temperet a Lachrimis?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>But to proceed, It having pleaſed God to purge this Land of ſuch Popiſh trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, and the Clergy at preſent able and induſtrious in preaching, and godly in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; Idolatry and Images removed leaving the ſucceſs, both of our prayers and preaching, to Gods mercifull and wiſe diſpoſing) the preaching of Gods word being the power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who can ſay but it may pleaſe God that this work, the great work of the <hi>Iews</hi> converſion may at this time by this power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Engine, and our prayers for the ſame end, be effected and accompliſhed, that it may, theſe things are to prove it?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Gods arm is not ſhortned,</hi> his will and power to bring this to paſs is the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His ſpirit and word are as powerful and readie as in former time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Who can ſhut when God opens?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115072:10"/>4. God hath and can remove the vail, and take away the heart of ſtone, and give them a heart of fleſh, to tremble at his word, he hath brought light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and converted as great and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſinners as they are.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Many of them have been converted, and the reſt ſhall; and oh! that the Lord would think upon <hi>Sion,</hi> for it pitieth thy ſervants to ſee her in the duſt. That's to the firſt.</p>
            <p>2. To be upright and juſt in our Contracts and bargains with them.</p>
            <p>The waies to joyn and cement one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to another are ſundrie, as unitie in Religion, publick marriages of Princes, leagues and confederacies, aſſiſtance in troubles, ſcarce any one more prevalent then publick and common intercourſe of merchandize and traffick, by this courſe the ſtock of one people, or a great part of it is tranſmitted to another, whereupon there is a great truſt &amp; credit given by each Nation to another, and uſually the breach of bargains and truſt is followed with a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115072:11"/>war; and therefore we ſhould have ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care to be faithfull to perform to our utmoſt, though it be to our loſs, what we bargain for: ſo the Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>He that maketh a bargain with his neighbour, and diſappoints him not, though it were to his own hinderance;</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul, Brethren defraud not one another in bargains:</hi> Contracts and Covenants are not to be violated, ſome miſchief and miſeries uſually enſue upon the violaters, as in that contract of the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> and that alſo made by <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> broken by <hi>Saul,</hi> ſeverely revenged upon <hi>Saul,</hi> and upon his bloody houſe. It was the diſgrace of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> that they were <hi>Foedi fragi,</hi> Truce-breakers, its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo by <hi>Paul; Rom.</hi> ch. 1. that amongſt many other things, the Heathens were <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when in trading, one Nation per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a principle of fidelitie, and junate honeſtie, it's a great motive, and a ſecret inward inforcing argument of the fearing of God in the heart, hereupon <hi>Moſes</hi> tels the Iſraelites, that the Nations about them when they heard, ſhall ſay, ſurely this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115072:11"/>is a wiſe underſtanding people; the credit and reputation of a Nation is Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>exalteth or eſtabliſheth a Nation,</hi> and Gods Scepter is by <hi>David</hi> termed <hi>a Scepter of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and it ſets out Chriſts glory, <hi>Thou haſt loved Righteouſneſs, Pſal.</hi> 45. and it is that which <hi>Abraham</hi> attributes to God, <hi>Shal not the Judge of all the world do Right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay then poſitively, that to forward and help on the long deſired, and prayed for converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> by admiſſion into <hi>England,</hi> we ſhould be carefull to be upright in all our doings, and dealings with them; they are a people of themſelves ſublime, and ſtrenuouſly ingenuous, and naturally addicted to trade and traffick; and truly 'tis a wonder how they ſhould, and how they do yet ſubſiſt, and grow rich, for my part I ſay, that conſidering their ſevere exiles, from one Country to Country, their taxes, impoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcations, pillages, ſtrippings, rifellings, by publick commands, by inſurrections ſeverall times, in ſeverall places, as alſo their wandrings from City to City, their deep payments for a new place, little or no pity ſhewed to them at their coming in,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115072:12"/>or abode in a place, but moſt accounting it lawfull to wrong or rob a <hi>Iew,</hi> beſides the ſeverall praemunires they have run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and their mulcts alwaies exceeding great, and exacted with ſeverity and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, by intruſted inferiour Officers: I ſay, 'tis a wonder to think how they ſhould have any thing left them to ſuſtain them, their incombes not viſibly much, no Crown Lands, ſcarce a foot of Land in a Country their own, no ſhips of publike traffick built or ſent out by them, no Collections of Charity made for them in any City or Country by Chriſtians, no beggars amongſt them; ſurly for &amp; certain, God makes them to encreaſe and abound in wealth, as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaies, <hi>Notwithſtanding, their Oppreſſors, and he ſuffered not their ſubſtance to decreaſe,</hi> and it may be ſaid of them, as it was at their firſt travelling out of <hi>Egypt, He brought them out alſo with Silver and Gold,</hi> for 'tis known they do yet abound with it, being able upon a ſudden to furniſh a Prince with treaſure, upon any occaſion; and ſome of the Kings of Chriſtendome have made too much uſe of them, though they never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed them, nay, the former Kings of <hi>England</hi> have had ſupplies many times out
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115072:12"/>of the <hi>Jews</hi> Coffers, and in requitall for true payment, baniſhed them the Land, upon ſome falſe ſuggeſtions or other, made by the Popiſh Prieſts in thoſe times againſt them; whereas indeed 'twas becauſe they being not able to repay them, they thought it a diſparagement to have ſuch Creditors live neer the Court.</p>
            <p>How they have been dealt withal by our Kings, and Princes, and Clergy, Nobles, and Commons, by oppreſſions, frauds, confiſcations, deep payments of vaſt and ſeverall ſums, our Chronicles largely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; 'tis ſtrange they venture again here, knowing how unjuſtly, unrighteouſly, unmercifully, they have been uſed, for certain tis, they have heard of the upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our preſent Governors, or elſe they would never deſire ſhelter under them, nor bring in ſuch a maſs of treaſure; and truſt them with it, had they not a great confidence of their integrity, and that the fear of God was grounded in their hearts, or elſe they believe that a people ſo much profeſſing Godlineſs muſt needs be civilly and religiouſly juſt, and upright. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good people of <hi>England,</hi> let them ſee your good works, that they may glorifie God on your behalfs. To proceed.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115072:13"/>
            <p>3. <hi>By our civil and gentle comportment, and love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in our markets, ſhops and meetings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religion heightens civility, a gentle affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble carriage graces and adorns our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; we ſhould ſhow our peaceable and meek diſpoſition, upon all occaſions; the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is excellent in his inſtructions and practice in this particular, <hi>To the Greek I became as a Greek, to the Jew I am become as a Iew, I became all things to all men, that by all means I might win ſome;</hi> the Apoſtle had ſuch ſpeciall regard to win both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that he framed his carriage ſo that it might win, not only his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but his comportment, his life and outward demeanor towards the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould be ſuch, and acted with that ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and complacency of behaviour, that by it he might win the <hi>Iews,</hi> were they to be won by this means then; and why not now? does the Apoſtle practiſe it as a ſure way to effect his end to win them to Chriſt? ſure the ſame carriage would (if uſed towards them) be as powerfull in our dayes: It's
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115072:13"/>ſaid of <hi>Moſes, that there was not ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meek man upon the face of the Earth;</hi> 'twas for certain, his meekneſs gained love, and authority; and made him ſo admired and beloved of the people. If ye bite and devour one another (ſaies the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) ye ſhall be bitten and devoured one of another; what the carriage of other Nations is towards the <hi>Jews,</hi> is known, and hiſtories make mention ſufficiently, even to the diſgrace of Chriſtianity, but tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Papal juriſdiction, yea, none ſo barbarous, and inſolent, and ſcornfull over them, as the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not being content with fleecing, but delighting to flay them; ſo in ſome Towns of <hi>Germany,</hi> as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lmes,</hi> and <hi>Wormbs,</hi> the people doe daily infeſt them with ribaldry language, and opprobrious Carriage, eſteeming them worſe then their dogs, ſetting dogs upon them as they paſs the ſtreets, curſing and railing upon them when they meet them, caſting dirt, and filthy naſtie dung upon their cloaths, and upon any ſeeming offence, nay, any falſe forged accuſation ſhall be enough to convene them with threats to turn them all out of their gates, and it muſt be accounted a favour if the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115072:14"/>Governors will be pleaſed to remit this puniſhment, and accept of ſome great ſum of mony for ſatisfaction: Moſt places being Popiſh, are cruel and unjuſt in their carriage to the poor <hi>Jews,</hi> abiding within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral juriſdictions, and can there be much, or any hopes of their Converſion from ſuch who aim at nothing leſs, nor intend them ſo much good; nay indeed, who are a means to hinder their Converſion?</p>
            <p>And to ſpeak truth to this particular, our Nation was in former time highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated with fury and malice againſt theſe poor people, but 'twas for certain the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſubtile practiſes of the Popiſh Prieſts, that incited the Kings, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Commons, by raiſing ſome lies or miſdemeanors committed by them; and this was practiſed uſually when the Kings were neceſſitated for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and to eaſe themſelves of the deep taxes and Impoſitions, the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould be accuſed, and ſo forc'd to pay great ſums to obtain a good eſteem, and to purchaſe their quiet and peace with the King, and to eſcape the violence and rage of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but if it pleaſe our Governors to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them into this Land, ſurely a meek &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115072:14"/>peaceable carriage will greatly grace our profeſſion of the Goſpel, and by Gods mercy in his due time work much, yea very much upon their hearts, and affection. To conclude the third branch of our firſt argu. I read in Gods word, that in that night the Children of Iſrael came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> 'tis obſerved in the Text, that amongſt all the noiſe and tumult, for they came out in haſt, yet there was not a Dog that moved his tongue throughout all the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> Certain it was a ſpecial commanding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, that not a Dog. 2. Though by nature fierce, though watchfull. 3. Not to bite, not to bark, yea, not to move his tongue againſt this people: I could wiſh that at their entrance here, the tongues and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pens of all vijulent and turbulent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits might be ſilent, if not of their own accord, yet by publique authority, and that <hi>Gamaliels</hi> advice may take place, take heed what you do to theſe men, for if this work be of God, it will ſurely ſtand, but if it be of men, it will fall, &amp;c. take heed leſt ye ſeem to fight againſt God; Let then our Shops and Shambles, our Exchange and Cuſtom-houſes, our Market-places &amp; high-waies be civilly &amp; ſoberly free; the Apoſtle
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115072:15"/>ſaies plainly, <hi>What ye buy in the ſhambles,</hi> &amp;c. Let no ſcruple be made of it; no nor any affront or diſgrace by any uncivill ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture or unjuſt Actions be offered to the buyer; buying or ſelling, being as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a <hi>Iew,</hi> as for a Chriſtian, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould have a care that they make not their good be evil ſpoken off, but to do as the Apoſtle admoniſhes, to give no <hi>offence to the Gentile, nor to the Jew,</hi> nor to lay a ſtumbling block in their way, but by their juſt and upright dealing, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and gentle behaviour towards them, endeavour their love and affection, which both, with the preaching of Gods Word; purely and ſolidly, may in Gods time win them to the faith: however, if our aimes come ſhort of our intendments, yet we are clear in the ſight of God; and if Chriſtians muſt take heed that they do not by meats &amp; drinks offend their weaker brother, much more muſt they be wary, not by idolatry and ſuperſtitious ſacrifices, to deſtroy theſe their Brethren, for whom, ſaies the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Chriſt dyed</hi> Though they be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, yet ſeeing they may belong to Gods love, offend them not, ſaies our Saviour.</p>
            <p>To proceed to our ſecond Argument, for their Admiſſion.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115072:15"/>
            <p>2. <hi>In Civill reſpects, and that proved by two things.</hi> 1. <hi>Their Relation to us in Nature.</hi> 2. Jure Gentium, <hi>by the Law of Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Relations are of deep concernment, true eſſentiall Relatives ſtand or fall together, none of neerer being, then thoſe that are naturall; therefore the infringers and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators of the Laws of Nature, have in all ages and Nations, been execrable and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; according to Nature every thing ſtrives to preſerve, and love, and to cheriſh his own kinde; and ſhall man of all things and creatures, hate or deſtroy it? and hath not God (ſaies the Apoſtle) <hi>of one blood made all mankinde?</hi> there's an Identity of Nature, not onely a ſtrict Relation: and now then, where (as the ſame Apoſtle ſaies) <hi>is the difference of the Jew, or of the Gentile?</hi> are we <hi>not all one?</hi> not only in Chriſt Jeſus, but alſo in Nature; we are all (ſaies Saint <hi>Paul his off-ſpring,</hi> we are all cut out of the ſame Rock; <hi>and God, who is rich in mercy, is the father of us all</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle) obſerve how the <hi>Jews</hi> did
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115072:16"/>wittily and lovingly acknowledge this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in that of the <hi>Canticles, We have a little Siſter who hath no breaſts, what ſhall we do for her, when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken of?</hi> who was meant by their little ſiſter? 'tis agreed by all Expoſitors, that it was the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and behold the Relation! <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> are termed <hi>Siſters,</hi> the greater, and the leſs; and who can but obſerve the Care and love of the One to the other? What ſhall we do for her? ſaies the text, ſhe is our Siſter our little Siſter, it ſtands us upon to take a Care of her, and to do her good in her day; and how can this <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ceaſe now? had the <hi>Jews</hi> ſuch a care for us, when we were little and ſmall, and ſhall we deſpiſe them now we are full grown, and in vigor &amp; ripeneſs of age, and hate them, becauſe they are elder, and have been for many years in miſery and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet are not out of it? Conſider what ſtrict notice God took of <hi>Eſaus</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, that he would not ſhew any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to his brother, but inſulted over him, and was hatefull towards him in the anguiſh of his ſpirit, what heavy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were denounced againſt him? and how can we which are Chriſtians look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Brethrens miſery, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115072:16"/>and compaſſion, and not fear the like, or a heavier Judgement will befall us, for that we had no tender bowels of Compaſſion and Charity towards them? what an unnaturall carriage is it, for a younger Brother not to ſuffer his elder Brother to come into his houſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is out, will keep him out, and perſecute him too with malice, and is ſo far from ſhewing mercy, that he is angry with them who afford lodging and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to him? and though he knows him in a ſtorm, is ſo far from inviting him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſhelter, that he had rather he ſhould periſh without, then he ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted In? ſhould not all Relations ſavour of, and be full of Love and Charity? Conſider well this ſerious and deep Relation in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and learn to put on Bowels of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and Compaſſion towards theſe poor Out-caſts of Iſrael; for as St. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayes well, <hi>Which of you ſeeing your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want, if you do not releive him, how dwells the Love of God in you?</hi> and if they ſhall be condemned at the Laſt day, for not taking a ſtranger In, what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them, who ſcornfully ſhut their own Brother Out? <hi>Abraham,</hi> the father
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115072:17"/>of the faithfull, urges this as a conducing Argument to <hi>Lot, Let us not fall out; for we are Brethren;</hi> he laies the Energie of his Argument upon the Relation of Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and how unſitting a ſpeech was <hi>Cains</hi> to God, concerning this Relation, <hi>Am I my Brothers k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eper?</hi> intimating that he ſhould have been ſo; and therefore <hi>Cains</hi> ſin, was a ſin againſt Naturall Relation: and admirable is that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ch. 58. When <hi>thou ſeeſt the poor that are caſt out, that thou bring them home to thine houſe, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine own fleſh.</hi> And though our Brethren the <hi>Jews</hi> at preſent are in a diſtreſſed condition, muſt they be totally rejected? who can ſay but they are caſt out, that we ſhould kindly take them In? and for certain 'tis, that they who will not admit them, do not pity their caſting out. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks divinely of their caſting out, and <hi>if their caſting</hi> or cutting off <hi>be our implanting In, if their fall</hi> be our fulneſs, <hi>what ſhall their reſtoring be?</hi> and we that are bound to help our neighbours Oxe or Aſs fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ditch, for certain are not debar'd to help our Brother out of miſery. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the ſecond Branch for their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that is,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115072:17"/>2. <hi>Jure Gentium,</hi> by the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>The ſtricteſt Law next to that of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is that of the Law of Nations, and under this are included all Publique <hi>Leagues,</hi> publique <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> publique <hi>Merchandizing</hi> and <hi>Commerce;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this is that Noble ſaying which our Saviour himſelf uſed, <hi>What ye would that men,</hi> any men, <hi>ſhould do unto you, ſo do unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets:</hi> Now by this Rule it will follow, that if we in miſery and calamity would not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied friendſhip and ſuccour, we then ought not to deny the ſame to other men, and if we would not be excluded from ſhelter and favour, we ſhould not deny it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; no, not to the <hi>Jews,</hi> for they being a Noble part of the univerſall body, why ſhould one member exclude, or deny ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to another? for as the Apoſtle hath ſaid elegantlie, that <hi>even thoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which ſeem to be leſs comely hath God put moſt comelineſs on,</hi> that there ſhould <hi>be no Schiſm in the Body;</hi> and therefore the head cannot ſay to the foot; <hi>I have no need of thee,</hi> or if the eye, or any other ſuperiour member ſhould ſay uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115072:18"/>and unchriſtianly to another, <hi>I have no need of thee, is it not therefore of the body?</hi> nay, even thoſe members which ſeem leſs neceſſary, may yet be found, not onely comelie, but neceſſary for the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole: and therefore, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joſeph, ſend for thy Father and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and let them dwell amongſt us,</hi> which was done accordingly, <hi>Jacob</hi> ſued not for it, yet was admitted into the Land, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any murmuring or hatred of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, till in length of time, by the Tyranny and policy of another King, who <hi>knew not Joſeph,</hi> they were unjuſtlie and unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vexed and oppreſſed: but for certain 'tis, at their Coming In, no man was againſt it, neither is it expreſſed that they did any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie, nor is there any complaint made, that they made victuals dear, or were a burthen to the Land, and yet they were there 430. years, and were increaſed from 70 or 75. at moſt, to 600000. men, beſides women and children, which to all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, amounted to above a million of Souls; ſhall we be leſs charitable in theſe times to that Nation then <hi>Egypt</hi> was? or have we any reaſon, in any civill reſpect, to denie them Commerce and trading with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115072:18"/>us, &amp; amongſt us? Certainly we may afford it to them by the Law of Nature and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But I goe on; and ſay, that the <hi>Jews</hi> may be admitted into <hi>England,</hi> and that,</p>
            <p>3. <hi>By Ties of Religion on our parts, and ſo,</hi> 1. <hi>We are to deſire, pray for, and further their Converſion and Calling.</hi> 2. <hi>We are earneſtly to pray for their Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the Hopes of this peoples <hi>Converſion</hi> by the means afore mentioned, may incite us, and though the Law of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> may invite us, yet this Tye, and bond of <hi>Religion,</hi> may, and doth ſeem ſpiritually to force us to afford them admittance into <hi>England;</hi> all or moſt of our Pulpits, I am ſure the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> amongſt our Miniſters do, (and in truth do but what they ought to do) pray for the <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Converſion</hi> of the <hi>Iews,</hi> ſome with larger and more <hi>patheticall</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions then others; but ſurelie their prayers, if they be void of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> too, any man of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding will ſay they are but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115072:19"/>vain and hypocriticall before God: I do not abſolutely accuſe them, yet by their concluſions; in denying them a brotherly Admittance amongſt us, 'tis deeply ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected they pray not ſo effectually, and intentionally as they ought, for can it be thought that they pray in <hi>faith,</hi> when as yet all know <hi>faith</hi> doth work by <hi>love;</hi> In <hi>faith</hi> we ſay, when as this people live as yet, in Countries ſubject to <hi>Turks, Infidels,</hi> and Idolatrous <hi>Papiſts,</hi> where no means is uſed, no ordinarie means, but rather all done contrary to any ſuch intention, how can they in <hi>faith</hi> expect their <hi>Converſion</hi> under ſuch darkneſs, Tyranny, and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? <hi>How can they believe except they hear? and how can they hear without a Preacher? and how can they preach except they be ſent?</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle; now our Preachers holding the Popiſh Clergies <hi>Miſſion</hi> not lawful, but <hi>Anti-chriſtian;</hi> can they believe that <hi>Anti-chriſt</hi> will convert to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and though ſome of them preach, yet, tis ſeldome, and then full of fables, ſtories, and Legends of ſome miracles done by <hi>Saints,</hi> of no efficacy to ſtir up the <hi>ſoul</hi> to that height, as to work <hi>Repentance</hi> or <hi>Converſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115072:19"/>
            <p>And ſecondly, how can they pray in <hi>Charity</hi> when as they will not admit this people into their Congregations, nay, not into the Nation, that yet they might come out from thoſe dark dens of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and Heatheniſh <hi>Idolatry</hi> to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Gods word powerfully taught; and to ſee the juſt and upright lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations of men who profeſs ſo much godlineſs as at preſent <hi>England</hi> doth; theſe mens prayers, and intentions ſhould agree, and then certainly they would be glad to hear that God had put it into the hearts of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to deſire ſuch a thing at the hands of our preſent Governours, with leaving the Iſſue to God, and the means.</p>
            <p>But for their ſpeedier <hi>Converſion</hi> the Apoſtle ſaies, they muſt <hi>hear,</hi> and hearing implies they muſt not be ſhut out of the Land, but admitted, into it, and into our ſocieties; it ſeems a <hi>Riddle,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Ridiculous</hi> to hope the <hi>Converſion</hi> of that people, with whom they never <hi>converſe</hi> or <hi>confer;</hi> Conference and Converſation being two main helps to further <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they had heard <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon, they heard it then, the Text ſaies,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115072:20"/>then they came to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> there's their <hi>Conference,</hi> and they <hi>continued with the Apoſtles,</hi> there's their <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> too. Many other examples might be produced; I wiſh all Preachers, and others, who are againſt their Coming <hi>In,</hi> to lay this to heart, and to take heed that by being againſt their Coming <hi>In,</hi> they do not make their <hi>prayers</hi> void, and ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; their <hi>prayers</hi> being for them, their <hi>Actions</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing we do <hi>Actually</hi> pray for their <hi>Calling</hi> and Converſion, which thing all learned men ſay ſhall be effected; nay, the Scriptures are full for it, as ſhall appear, yet <hi>de modo,</hi> of the manner of it there is not a generall Conſent, whether it ſhall be <hi>a Locis migrando;</hi> or, <hi>in Locis credendo,</hi> by travelling from all Countries into which they are ſcattered into, and unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again; or by believing in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in the places into which they are ſo ſcattered and diſperſt: Much might here be ſaid on both parts, but not intending Controverſies in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe, we interpoſe not in it.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115072:20"/>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſing himſelf in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to the full, ſaith, <hi>Rom. ch.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire, and prayer to God for Iſraelis, that they may be ſaved, for I bear them record, that they have a zeal of God;</hi> there is heat, and therefore hopes of it: and the Apoſtle ſaies, he did <hi>heartily</hi> and trulie deſire it, and thereupon prayed for it, and how he could even wiſh himſelf <hi>accurſed from Chriſt</hi> for <hi>his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſake;</hi> and the Prophet <hi>David</hi> prayes thus: Oh that thou wouldſt <hi>bring home thy people, as thou didſt ſometimes, from the depth of the Sea!</hi> and, <hi>O think upon</hi> Sion, <hi>and have mercy upon her, for it grieveth and pitieth thy ſervants to ſee her in the duſt!</hi> nay, our Saviour himſelf, it is ſaid of him, that he <hi>prayed for theſe tranſgreſſors,</hi> Eſa. 53. and upon the Croſs, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do;</hi> which he meant of their Sin, in mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering him, the <hi>Prince of Life,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> tells them, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. and <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> ch. 7. prayes, <hi>Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge;</hi> not onelie the ſin of ſtoning him, but that their ſin of <hi>Crucifying Chriſt;</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> took great pains to work their <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> &amp; <hi>Converſion,</hi> by preaching zealouſly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115072:21"/>unto them, and did convert 1000s of them, and did all theſe holy and eminent men labour to further this? why then ſhould not we? that we ſhould, I ſay, for <hi>our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and theirs ſhall be both together,</hi> not they without us, nor we without them ſhall be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>v. ult,</hi> we ſhall not come to the ſtature of a perfect man in Chriſt, God being the God both of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſtir us up therefore to be earneſt with God to help on the <hi>Jews Converſion,</hi> conſider <hi>Davids</hi> care, the <hi>Prophets</hi> ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſivelie ſent to this people for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, our bleſſed Lord took great pains, and wrought many Miracles, gave them divers inſtructions, as <hi>work while ye have the light; why ſtand ye here idle? I would have gathered thee O Jeruſalem, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens; I have called and cryed all the day, and O that thou hadſt known!</hi> and what <hi>could I have done more for my Vineyard?</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> how vigorous and induſtrious to bring them to <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Oh let there be in us the ſame ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to do this people good, <hi>for God is able to graft them in again:</hi> O let it never be ſaid of us, that Gods people, his Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115072:21"/>people, <hi>of whom according to the fleſh Chriſt Ieſus came,</hi> being ſad and grieved in ſpirit, travelling from one City to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, being few in Number, hearing that the Goſpel was purely preached <hi>here,</hi> that <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>uprightneſs</hi> flouriſhed <hi>here,</hi> that God had done great things <hi>here,</hi> humbly deſired to come In <hi>here,</hi> as hoping and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving they ſhould find ſome reſt <hi>here,</hi> and that they ſhould finde a <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> people <hi>here,</hi> with gracious and wiſe Governours <hi>here;</hi> let it I ſay never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that <hi>England rejected</hi> them, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would not give <hi>Admiſſion</hi> to Gods Ancient <hi>heritage. England</hi> denyed them to hear Gods holy Word, whereby they might be ſaved; who can ſay what Gods <hi>Intendments</hi> may be? whether or no <hi>we</hi> may not have the <hi>Credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>greateſt,</hi> and <hi>firſt</hi> Comfort of their happy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with us in the ſame <hi>faith</hi> in the <hi>Lord Jeſus?</hi> and why may not they acknowledge the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Nation? me thinks I hear them ſay, Bleſſed be God that hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us from our Enemies; and who hath found out a <hi>place</hi> of ſafety and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us? Oh how have we been trod on, ſcorned, abuſed, fleeced, and butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115072:22"/>in many other places, but yet at laſt God lent us a <hi>ſhelter,</hi> even <hi>England; England</hi> we ſay, where we finde Comfort for ſouls and bodies; <hi>England,</hi> who holds up Gods glory, and fights the Lords battels; <hi>England,</hi> which is ſo famous for <hi>Piety,</hi> where we have received <hi>faith</hi> to believe and imbrace the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> Oh bleſſed be God; who now of late hath thus mercifully viſited, and brought us out of thick darkneſs, into marvellous light, by the power of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of his dear Son, our precious Saviour, and Eternall, and Mercifull Redeemer, ſo plentifully, and ſo powerfully preached in <hi>England!</hi> O what a Comfort and Credit will this be to our Nation, that <hi>our</hi> Righteouſneſs, <hi>our</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Meekneſs, <hi>our</hi> zeal for Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>our</hi> Care for the Goſpel, <hi>our</hi> holineſs of Converſation, have been provokers, and ſtirrers up of the <hi>Jews;</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in the ſame Caſe, <hi>that by theſe I might provoke the Jews</hi> to the like, and ſo <hi>we</hi> to be the Gracious Inſtruments under God, for their happy deliverance from that blindneſs, and hardneſs of heart, under which at preſent they do ſo heavily groan, and ſigh.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115072:22"/>
            <p>4. <hi>By the Practice of many other Countries, Provinces, and free Cities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This fourth Argument is drawn from <hi>Practice,</hi> a good way of Argumentation; for though Gods word ſaies that we muſt not <hi>follow a Multitude to do Evill;</hi> yet its a ſhame on the other ſide, if that having ſuch a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes</hi> before us, we ſhould not at all be moved, and is it not a ſhame that the very Heathens and Infidels do yet ſhew <hi>mercy,</hi> and ſome love to theſe people of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who yet do it at beſt, either by the all-ruling <hi>wiſdome</hi> and power of God, forceably working their hearts to this end, they not knowing the Word of God? what theſe people are, or how, or when they ſhall be converted; nay, not truly knowing that ever they ſhall be <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> or yet what the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of Chriſt is unto which they ſhall be <hi>joyned,</hi> or elſe, ſecondly, becauſe they finde profit and gains, by ſuffering the <hi>Iews</hi> amongſt them, or upon any pretended injurious <hi>Act</hi> done by them; both their <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> are lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the <hi>One</hi> to death, the <hi>other</hi> to Confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as is to be ſeen in that bloody inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115072:23"/>
               <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Haman</hi> in King <hi>Aſhuerus</hi> time, to have been put in Execution had not God in his Infinite wiſdome and mercy to that people then prevented it.</p>
            <p>Yet any one that knows that Hiſtorie cannot but read that the <hi>Jews</hi> did live with, and amongſt thoſe <hi>Perſians,</hi> in a 127. Provinces without <hi>Let</hi> or <hi>Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and had free trading in <hi>all</hi> places, nay, even at <hi>Court</hi> too, for <hi>Mordecai</hi> is ſaid to ſit at the Court Gate untill <hi>Haman</hi> moved with prid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and malice intended not only Confiſcation of <hi>Eſtates,</hi> but their <hi>lives</hi> to boot; and indeed the politique and Cruell <hi>Counſellors</hi> of Covetous and ambitious <hi>Emperors</hi> and Kings, knowing and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the great wealth of the <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> by Gods bleſſing; have perſwaded their maſters (and any argument will ſerve a Covetous minde) to take and rake the <hi>Jews</hi> wealth into their treaſuries, when as they ſuppoſe a Crime committed againſt their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Lawes;</hi> ſo that to ſpeak truth it hath been the Riches and Monies of the <hi>Iews</hi> that have rendred them to puniſhments, and death it ſelf in thoſe Heathen Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, not their violation of their <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> and yet the <hi>Perſians</hi> then did, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115072:23"/>to this day admit them not only into their <hi>Countries,</hi> but alſo into their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels</hi> and <hi>Commiſſions;</hi> and have and do yet finde of them admirable, judicious, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet and valorous <hi>perſons,</hi> for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of publike affairs, either for <hi>way</hi> or <hi>peace:</hi> nay, let me ſpeak (and I will ſpeak but the truth) thoſe great and populous <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> though yet not brought to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> yet they who afford the <hi>Jews,</hi> I ſay the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>freeſt</hi> habitation <hi>largeſt</hi> priviledges, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the <hi>leaſt</hi> burthens and taxes, the <hi>feweſt</hi> vexations, who deal the <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt justly</hi> and favourably to them, who truſt them <hi>moſt,</hi> and torment them <hi>leaſt,</hi> thoſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons flouriſh <hi>moſt,</hi> abound in <hi>wealth,</hi> in <hi>ſtrength,</hi> in largeneſs of <hi>Empire</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to this very day above others their Neighbour Princes about them; as though one may ſay, that which God promiſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> is really fulfilled to this very day; <hi>I will bleſs them that bleſs thee, and I will Curſe them that Curſe thee;</hi> that is, thoſe people that ſhew kindneſs to them that ſhall come out of thy loynes, I will bleſs, but thoſe that ſhall be Cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, and oppreſſors of them, I will
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115072:24"/>Curſe; 'tis not the meaning, nor doth any <hi>Expoſitor</hi> or Commentator upon that <hi>Text,</hi> reſtrain the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> or <hi>Curſing</hi> to <hi>Abrahams perſon</hi> onely, but to all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Iews,</hi> whoſe father <hi>Abraham</hi> was, as they told our Saviour in St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpel, <hi>We have</hi> Abraham <hi>to our father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Nation that we will mention, is that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> populous and Potent for <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Arts,</hi> yet enemies to Jeſus Chriſt, a people apt to gain wealth, and augment their vaſt Empire, ſowre and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick of diſpoſition, yet even theſe have from their firſt Riſe, to their height, in which they now are; ſuffered the <hi>Jews</hi> amongſt them, and in ſome places with large Immunities, not debarring them their richeſt Kingdomes to Inhabit, nor their wealthieſt Cities to trade and traffick in; witneſs all <hi>Egypt,</hi> and therein <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> all <hi>Greece,</hi> and therein <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> it ſelf, the <hi>Metropolis,</hi> nay, all <hi>Aſia,</hi> and not one City in all <hi>that</hi> largeſt, fruitfull, moſt ſpacious, and opulenteſt part of the world, but the <hi>Jews</hi> have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to dwell, exerciſe their trade, nay, not debar'd <hi>one</hi> particular Town by any publike <hi>Edict</hi> of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperor, and all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115072:24"/>this done without any murmuring or repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the naturall born <hi>Turks,</hi> nay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mutinies, plots, treaſons, or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, practiſed by the <hi>Iews</hi> in all the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>I do not ſay, but that the <hi>Iews</hi> in many places, and at ſundry times have been (but it was by the falſe information of Clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Enemies (as they are very Common) to ſome <hi>Baſhaw, Vizier,</hi> or <hi>Viceroy,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Covetouſneſs, Ambition, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice) I ſay the <hi>Iews</hi> have been many of them ſtrangled, and deeply puniſhed by ſevere mulcts of their purſe, but this done Commonly without the Conſent or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Grand Seigneur,</hi> and when the <hi>Jews</hi> have complained, they have had ſure, and juſt, and ſpeedy remedie againſt the falſ Informer, if known, and againſt the <hi>Chief</hi> Officer, who did the injurie, but ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances fall ſeldome, and when acted, Puniſhed.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, the <hi>Jews</hi> have liberty to dwell where they pleaſe, to trade in what Country they pleaſe, to travell whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they pleaſe, to return in peace when they pleaſe; have freedome of Markets, Fairs, Merchandize of all ſorts, without
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115072:25"/>any controule, or trouble, and yet this Nation of the <hi>Turks</hi> thrives, grows Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and rich every where: Victuals of all ſorts plentifull, no ſcarcity of any thing uſefull for mankinde; the <hi>Turks</hi> complain not that the Iews eat up their proviſion, hinder their trade, or are any way trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to them, which evill (amongſt ſuch a <hi>Confluence</hi> of mankind, of ſuch ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and quick Natures) would eaſily be found, and remedied to the full, to the utter ruine and deſtruction of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe throats and eſtates lies open to any affront that ſhall be commanded to be offered; and ſince theſe people finde <hi>ſuch</hi> help, ſhelter, relief, and ſubſiſtence by trading and trafficking amongſt theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Heathens,</hi> will Chriſtians be <hi>Inferiour</hi> to them in <hi>Acts</hi> of Humanity and Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; <hi>Horreſco referens,</hi>— tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> publiſh it not in the ſtreets of <hi>Aske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> that Heathens ſhould <hi>exceed</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in harbouring and foſtering Strangers; but I proceed, and come into <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therein we finde <hi>Hungaria</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains them, <hi>Germany</hi> harbours them, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> till theſe wars, and <hi>Sweden</hi> trades with them, <hi>Denmark</hi> affords them habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115072:25"/>and <hi>Synagogues, Italy</hi> loves them, <hi>Holland</hi> approves them, <hi>Hamburgh, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> and moſt of the Imperial <hi>Hans-towns</hi> invite them <hi>In;</hi> and yet in all theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and places, who admit them, there is <hi>no</hi> diſturbance in Government, <hi>no</hi> Civil or Inbred Commotions, <hi>no</hi> popular Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Magiſtrates, about the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor any the leaſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence taken at the <hi>Jew,</hi> but live quietly and peaceably together, the Magiſtrate <hi>protecting,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> obeying his <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and injunctions.</p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> with his divelliſh and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Inquiſition, looks a ſquint at them, and uſes them as he doth <hi>other</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the Proteſtant Religion, without <hi>any</hi> Mercy or Equity; and what wonder is it, if theſe poor people not liking the uſage, do begin to grow wiſe, by forſaking his territories? we may ſay, as <hi>Solomon</hi> doth, the very <hi>mercies of the wicked are cruel,</hi> and ſo are the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> we may trace them by their <hi>bloody</hi> footſteps, in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and all other Countries where they could get footing or Soveraignty, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inhumane Butcheries of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> by that unſatiable <hi>Blood-hound,</hi> the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115072:26"/>
               <hi>Duke of Alva</hi> forced the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> with the help of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to break his teeth, and cut his pawes, or elſe long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, he had ſhewed them the ſtrength &amp; length of his <hi>Catholike Inquiſition</hi> for blood; He who never ſpared <hi>any</hi> that came into his clutches, no marvell if he ſhow his malice againſt theſe poor people the <hi>Jews,</hi> by burning, racking, and torturing of them for <hi>Religion</hi> (as he pretends) though he is as void of it, as they.</p>
            <p>But not to take Example from ſuch a Tyrant, Let <hi>England</hi> ſhew it ſelf a Nation profeſſing and upholding godlineſs, and ſo rather give Example to others, by being ready and cheerfull to harbour them that are Caſt <hi>Out,</hi> and to ſhew mercy to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, as knowing God himſelf will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our <hi>Labours</hi> in this kind, and laying deeply to our heart, the Infinite Love of God to us, when we our ſelves were (as the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Strangers,</hi> and <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies too;</hi> then did God Call us <hi>In,</hi> Into Grace, and Favour, and Mercy in his Son; when we wandred, and were wearied with the burthen of ſin, God took off our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and made us free, free Citizens, and Co-heirs with the Saints, nay, <hi>with his own
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115072:26"/>Son, Rom.</hi> ch. 8. nay, being Enemies, he reconciled himſelf to us by his Son; behold, <hi>he hath ſhewed us what is good!</hi> and therefore we ſhould goe and doe ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; It being an <hi>Act</hi> ſo full of Mercy, having ſo much of God in it; and theſe poor <hi>Strangers</hi> begging at our doors for a favourable, Charitable, and Chriſtian <hi>Admiſſion</hi> amongſt us, I ſay at preſent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring it at our hands: and that brings in our fifth Argument.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115072:27"/>
            <p>5. <hi>From Ties of Naturall Affection, and ſo,</hi> 1. <hi>To entertain St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gers, and that without reſpect of perſons.</hi> 2. <hi>To reward Evil with Good.</hi> 3. <hi>Not to ſuſpect them.</hi> 4. <hi>Nor to aggravate former long buried faults.</hi> 5. <hi>To forgive and forget all former Acts, and cover all with Chriſtian Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument ſtands in force, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Antiquity, and Gods Word: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are innate and powerfull in the ſoul, they are pullies, and will draw, and elevate the ſoul; take away naturall Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and what differs Man from Beaſts? nay, a man without it is inferiour to the Beaſt, even the cruelleſt, and moſt ſavage <hi>Tygers, Lions, Wolves,</hi> and <hi>Bears,</hi> none of theſe but love, and cheriſh their young <hi>Ones</hi> with care and Induſtry, the Scripture ſaies of the men that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>David,</hi> they were <hi>all like Bears
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115072:27"/>rob'd of their whelps,</hi> not to be met or medled withall, without danger of being torn in pieces, if they want, or be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their young <hi>Ones;</hi> and are theſe ſo affectionate, what ſhould <hi>man</hi> be then? nay, what ſhould a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> be? It is a fault the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> laies to the very <hi>Gentiles</hi> charge, that they were <hi>without Naturall Affection, Rom.</hi> ch. 1. but ſpeaking to Chriſtians, he ſaith thus; But <hi>ye Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, put on Bowels of tender Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Love, Meekneſs, Charity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If ye have any Bowels, fulfill my Joy,</hi> Phil. 2.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Now for certain, as 'tis our duty to be ſuch qualified, mercifull perſons, let us ſhow it in entertaining Strangers, and that <hi>without reſpect of perſons,</hi> whither <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Cornelius, of a truth God is no reſpecter of perſons, But in every Nation, he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> Act. 10. Now the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>There is no difference between the Jew and the Gentile, Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>for the ſame Lord over All, is rich unto All;</hi> that is, as well to <hi>Jew</hi> as to <hi>Gentile;</hi> now if there be none, nor God makes none, why
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115072:28"/>ſhould we put any difference? entertain them therefore, though Strangers, for ſo did <hi>Abraham</hi> entertain <hi>Angels, Heb.</hi> 13. It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he ſtood in the Tent door to wait for Strangers, and of <hi>Lot,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>he ſate in the Gate,</hi> and when two Angels (as Strangers) came, <hi>Lot</hi> went to meet them, and bowed to the ground, and what language gave he to them? <hi>O my Lord, turn into your Servants houſe, I pray you, and tarry there all night, and waſh your feet;</hi> and when they ſaid nay, <hi>He preſſed greatly</hi> upon them, and <hi>made them a Feaſt;</hi> and when the wicked <hi>Sodomites</hi> came to offer violence, He Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, intercedes ſtrongly for their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, and protection, by noble and force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arguments; ſeeming to condeſcend too too much to their Impudence and Bruitiſhneſs, then Strangers ſhould be injured and wronged. We may ſee by this how the holieſt, and godlieſt minded men did count it their comfort, their honour and delight, to afford Strangers kinde <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into</hi> their Houſes and Tents, and ſhall we at preſent debar them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them? and if our excluding them ſhould grieve and vex them, are not we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115072:28"/>guilty of Gods anger, and breach of his Word? <hi>Vex not a Stranger;</hi> however, we make our ſelves unlike to God, for <hi>Pſalm</hi> 146. <hi>v.</hi> 8. 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Lord preſerveth the Strangers,</hi> and ſhall we ſuffer them to periſh for want of Admittance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will conclude this with that Noble and Charitable direction of Mr.</hi> Peters, <hi>in his Book, entituled,</hi> Good work for a Good Magiſtrate, pag. 2. S. 6. <q>We ſhould give <hi>freedom of dwelling, trading and protection (mercy alſo) to all Strangers,</hi> to make little or no difference, as the Lord of old commanded his people, and promiſed to bleſs them for it; and this will enrich a Nation mightily, as we ſee in <hi>Holland,</hi> and not hurt any Natives, as envious perſons think, and can by good reaſons be proved;</q> 
               <hi>and quotes theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture for it.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.33, 34. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.21.</q> 
               <hi>worthy the Reading, to move you to harbour Strangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> at page 53. S. 5. <hi>the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſpeaks ſolidly,</hi> concerning <hi>Criminall</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> things. <q>Let no difference be made between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or Natives, in either <hi>Criminall</hi> or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115072:29"/>
                  <hi>Civil</hi> things, for ſo hath God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and by this means ſhall the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours be true fathers of Humanity, and it will mightily populate and enrich the Common-wealth, when the Oppreſſed in any other Country know where to go dwell under ſo juſt Government, with freedome from Oppreſſion:</q> 
               <hi>and theſe places are quoted for proof,</hi> 
               <q>Deut. 1.16, 17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.23. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At page 90. Sect. 6. <hi>He wiſely and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſets down theſe words:</hi> 
               <q>Let for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raingners, and all Strangers, <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathens, have full, as juſt, ſpeedy, and cheap Juſtice as any, ſo ſhall <hi>All</hi> Nations tell what the Lord hath done for you, and how will Riches flow In?</q> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, Naturall Affections bids us to do good againſt Evill, <hi>Be,</hi> ſaies the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>kindly affectioned one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with Brotherly Love,</hi> Rom. 12.10. &amp; v. 17. the Apoſtle addes this, <hi>Recompence no man Evil with Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe that ſome or moſt of the Jews that lived here formerly, were not ſo good as they ſhould have been; might it not be for want of <hi>good</hi> Magiſtrates or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115072:29"/>'tis ſaid in St. <hi>Matthew</hi> his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>And the people did as they were taught,</hi> had they been taught better, they would have done better; 'tis to be feared, the fault lies at our doors: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to do good againſt Evil, is to do as God himſelf doth, who cauſeth his Sun to ſhine, and his rain to fall both upon good and bad; and further, muſt it of neceſſity follow, that becauſe thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> were bad, that were here 300. or 200. years ſince, that theſe that come <hi>In</hi> now, muſt needs be ſo? we know that many of our fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were Popiſh, and the Land full of it then, but is it ſo ſtill; what a <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> may be by Gods good hand wrought, and brought about in a few years, is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen in our own in 14. and that might have been further heightened too; and therefore we are not to requite evil with evil, but if thine <hi>Enemy hunger, give him bread, if he thirſt, give him drink;</hi> and as our bleſſed Saviour hath it in his Sermon upon the Mount: <hi>But I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpightfully uſe, and perſecute you,</hi> that you <hi>may be the Children of your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115072:30"/>Father which is in Heaven: Matth.</hi> 5.44, 54. Look well to the performing of this.</p>
            <p>Next, as we are to do good againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: ſo are we not to ſupect them: it's the nature of true charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>To think no evil, David</hi> ſpeaks of wicked men they <hi>were in fear, where no fear was: (id eſt)</hi> when there was no cauſe of fear, ſuſpitious perſons are ill to bee judges; <hi>perfest love caſteth out fear,</hi> and where fear is, there is no perfect love, ſo ſays <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.18. why then ſhould we fear or ſuſpect them? it is becauſe their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors were evil, or becauſe theſe are thought to be nought, or that they may do us hurt; for the firſt many a bad father may have a good ſon, was not <hi>Ahaz</hi> father to good King <hi>Ezekiah?</hi> and <hi>Amon</hi> a wicked fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet <hi>Joſiah</hi> his ſon was a godly, zealous King, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.29. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.34. Were not the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in one Generation, bad, and in another holy and good? are not all ſtates ſubject to alteration and chang? we are not therefore to ſuſpect this generation, becauſe of the former; <hi>Malus cultura fit bonus,</hi> An evill man by due
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115072:30"/>order and government is made good; to the ſecond, I ſay, ill thoughts are the froth of the ſoul; if they be evill, you muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have it by knowledge or hearſay; ſay not, what you know not; and <hi>take not up a falſe Report:</hi> to lay a ſcandall upon a <hi>Nation,</hi> is not a light matter, they may perhaps not be ſo good as they ſhould, yet they may not be ſo bad as they are accounted. All is not Gold of <hi>Ophyr,</hi> yet may be uſed; I do not wonder ſo much that they have Vice, but I wonder that they ſhould retain any vertue, being ſo toſt from place to place, driven to ſuch extremities and exigencies, <hi>&amp; neceſſitas ſoepe cogit ad turpia,</hi> beſides what comes by contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>places</hi> where they live; they that live in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> are reputed the worſt, a poor cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit for thoſe Nations that make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves patterns for <hi>Iews</hi> to ſin by; for the third, of doing us Hurt; to our perſons they dare not, to our eſtates they cannot; can they that are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, out-ſtrip us in our own
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115072:31"/>wayes? very improbable: but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>As we are not to ſuſpect them, ſo much leſs not to aggravate long buried things; there are a ſort of men, that are always skilfull in <hi>multiplying</hi> this way; 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly thing, alwaies to be raking among the graves of the dead; our Saviour ſaies, <hi>ſufficient to the day, is the Evil thereof:</hi> ſo certain is it, with that of a moneth, or a year, or a generation; an <hi>Act</hi> of Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or an <hi>Amneſty</hi> would do well in this point; 'tis obſerved of thoſe two men <hi>poſſeſſed with devils,</hi> 'tis ſaid of them, <hi>that they lived among the graves,</hi> and were <hi>ſo fierce, that no man could paſs that way,</hi> Mat. 8.28. ſuch certain, who live by tearing up tombes of the dead that are buried, and their names out of minde, with their faults while they lived; aggravated with additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; certainly I ſay, they may be ſaid to be diveliſh men, and fierce men, that would have no man paſs quietly by them, but are ready to tear him in his good name, &amp;c. ſurely ſuch as raile at, and revile the poor <hi>Jews,</hi> for to hinder their <hi>Coming In,</hi> that rage, that are mad, that drive ſo furiouſly like <hi>Jehu,</hi> are they not like, too too like
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115072:31"/>thoſe men (I ſay) who were poſſeſſed, and knew not indeed <hi>what ſpirit they are off?</hi> theſe are like the raging Sea, caſting out its dirt and mire; they ſhould remember that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, 'tis <hi>the Honour of a Prince to paſs by offences;</hi> that love covers, not diſcovers a multitude of ſins; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our own infirmities and ſins, againſt which we cannot be too active, to hinder their <hi>Coming In,</hi> and living <hi>In,</hi> yes, and Ruling <hi>In</hi> our Souls; 'tis ill to give theſe admittance, 'tis good wiſdome to write againſt theſe, to ſtrive againſt theſe; but as for to hinder by writing or railing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> argues but little wit, and leſs wiſdome: ſo I come to the next Branch of Naturall Affection, which is indeed the chief, and the glory of Chriſtianity, if practiſed towards the <hi>Jews</hi> as it ought.</p>
            <p>And that is, to <hi>forgive</hi> and <hi>forget</hi> what is paſt, fully and freely, and to cover all with <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> And me thinks our Saviour argues ſublimely in this point, <hi>If thy Brother offend thee, forgive him,</hi> if he offends ſeventy ſeven times, uſe the ſame remedy, forgive him, if ye <hi>will not forgive men their treſpaſſes, neither will your
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115072:32"/>heavenly father forgive you,</hi> Mat. 6. thou evil and wicked Servant, I forgave thee all thy debt, which thou couldſt never have paid me, oughſt not thou to have had Compaſſion on thy brother and fellow ſervant, and have forgiven him? take him ſaies our Saviour, and caſt him into priſon, he ſhall not come forth, till he pay the utmoſt farthing. I leave the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this, to thoſe who ſuſpitiouſly brand the <hi>Jews</hi> with Abundance of foule faults, but they that are free ſhould throw the firſt ſtone, not they that are guilty; why do any rail againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they are in the ſame condemnation? let theſe either excuſe themſelves from ſin, or ceaſe to accuſe the <hi>Jews</hi> of theirs; a <hi>Dead</hi> carcaſe is to be buried for <hi>Civility</hi> and Comelineſs, <hi>ſuffer me to bury my dead,</hi> the ſins of the <hi>Iews,</hi> were they great, yet in 200 or 150. years they may die, and ſo to be buried <hi>as a dead man, out of minde;</hi> Lord, ſaies <hi>Martha,</hi> he hath been dead and buried four dayes, and ſtinketh, and thereby ſeemed to perſwade our Saviour not to medale with him; certainly, then we ſhould not meddle with thoſe <hi>Iews,</hi> who have been buried 400. years, if yet they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115072:32"/>were faulty: We uſe to cover an ill ſavour, and keep far from it, and they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unclean which had <hi>touched any dead perſon;</hi> and therefore concerning what was done by the <hi>Iews</hi> towards us, or by us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them (for they were the ſufferers and looſers) let it be, I ſay, let it be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and forgiven; remembring that of St. <hi>Paul, Brethren, forgive one another, even as Chriſt hath forgiven you.</hi> Now follows the ſixth Argument for their Admiſſion into <hi>England,</hi> and that is,</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115072:33"/>
            <p>6. <hi>By our Trading, &amp; living with and amongſt other people, who are void of the knowledg of God, and Enemies to the Reformed Religion: As,</hi> 1. <hi>Heathens and Idolaters;</hi> 2. <hi>Popiſh and Superſtitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath a ſaying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. <hi>I wrote to you in an Epiſtle, not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with fornicators, yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous or Contentious, or Idolaters, for ſo you muſt go out of this world.</hi> This place right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood, doth not debar us trading with ſuch people or Nations as are Adict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to theſe <hi>Capital</hi> mentioned ſins, and therefore if we may trade with ſuch ſinful men, I ſay, why ſhould the <hi>Jewes</hi> only, of all other Nations, Tongues, and Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be excluded this ſo common, ſo allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Commerce, and Converſation? and yet it appears not that they are ſuch, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit they were, certainly there is no debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from this Text, but that they with,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115072:33"/>and amongſt us, and we with them, may trade freely; and if this ſhould follow, that we might not, many <hi>Clients</hi> would ſcarce find <hi>Lawyers</hi> to receive unjuſt <hi>Fees,</hi> which yet abound every where in our Lands, and we might go out of the world, if we ſhould only imploy Lawyers, who were free from theſe faults; for which of them are free from all or moſt of theſe Crimes?</p>
            <p>Men, eſpecially Merchants, their affairs being more abroad then at home, brings them into variety of company, and ſome with whom they trade, may be men of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute carriage, as <hi>Fornicators, Covetous,</hi> ſhall they not then trade with ſuch? Not ſo, ſayes the Apoſtle, for then <hi>you muſt go out of the world,</hi> you will want vent for your wares, for ſuch kind of people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, eſpecially did at that time at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuth,</hi> and all <hi>Greece</hi> over: Indeed thoſe particular ſins in the Apoſtles daies, were the ſhame of <hi>Greece,</hi> and proved the ruine of them by the <hi>Turks;</hi> 'twas to be wiſh'd that all the men of this world were free from theſe ſins, but ſince 'tis improbable, and impoſſible, you may trade with them, and deal with them in worldly matters,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115072:34"/>as <hi>buying</hi> and <hi>ſelling, paying</hi> and <hi>receiving</hi> of moneys, making <hi>accounts,</hi> with ſuch like; but if there be any that is a Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, a Member of the Church, who is ſuch a <hi>one,</hi> avoid him, eat not with him at the Table of the Lord, he is a ſtain and a ſhame too to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and power of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe:</hi> amongſt worldly men he is not ſo ſcandalous, nor ſo much noted, for <hi>the world will love her own;</hi> you may trade and exchange wares, but not learn or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe his vices, but if, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have nothing to do with him: Hence we obſerve; 1. <hi>That ſins in Profeſſors that are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, are to be ſhun'd.</hi> 2. <hi>That thoſe ſins which are ſcandalous in them, may yet not be ſo amongſt Tradeſmen and Merchants, and men of this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our preſent purpoſe, that though theſe were <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and unconverted, yet that did not hinder Traffick, with and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe the world as though you us'd it not; uſe</hi> it they might, but not comply with the ſins of perſons or places; Trading and Traffick is a part of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi> Juſtice, the lying, fraud, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diſſembling, extortion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not <hi>Eſſentials,</hi> no, nor fit <hi>Appendixes</hi> to it;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115072:34"/>ſin and vice are ſo far from conſtituting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man, that indeed they <hi>deface</hi> and diſgrace the <hi>beſt</hi> part of him, the <hi>Soul:</hi> I onely give this directory concluſion to our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Merchants and Factors, who go out young, that they would remember they go to barter commodities, now there's <hi>no commodity</hi> in ſins; they go out for to bring home goods, but there's <hi>no goodneſſe</hi> in ſin; they ſhould ſtrive to get Pearles, Precious Stones, and rich Jewels, Gold and Silver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but there's no luſtre, or beauty, nor riches in vices and ſins: they go out for Spices and Aromatick Drugs, fragrant and fruitful unguents, as Balm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſin has a ſtinking ſcent, and noyſome ſmell, there is no fruit, or true pleaſure, comes from it: trade, but keep <hi>faith,</hi> and a <hi>good conſcience;</hi> thoſe Ships come heavy loaden that are full of ſinners, ſin weighs heavy in payment, though light in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; remember, I ſay, all you that go to the <hi>Indies, Perſia, Turkie, Greece, Italy,</hi> and <hi>France, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Trading then being lawful with all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if it were not, ſurely the Apoſtle would not have allowed a thing of <hi>higher</hi> concernment then Trafficking with <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115072:35"/>and <hi>Heathens,</hi> and that is <hi>Marriage;</hi> of that he ſayes expreſly, <hi>What knoweſt thou, Oh man, but thou mayeſt ſave thy unbelieving wife;</hi> and ſo againe, <hi>What knoweſt thou, O wife, but that thou mayeſt ſave thy unbelieving husband.</hi> Now for certain, marriage is much higher then only trading, if the <hi>greater</hi> be allowed, the <hi>leſs</hi> is included.</p>
            <p>And now to ſpeak to this particular, are the <hi>Jews</hi> ſuch ſinners above all others, that only they muſt be excluded? ſure I am that their Capital Sin was, and is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all, to be the <hi>Crucifying of Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord of Life.</hi> Now our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf did heartily pray for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of that, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi> To ſay he was not <hi>heard,</hi> and his Petition not granted, is impious and deſperate blaſphemy; and if granted, as it was, ſure they are not ſuch deteſtable creatures as they are proclaimed in Prin; 'twas to be wiſh'd he had made a longer <hi>demurrer,</hi> and not vented ſuch ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational ſpleen and malice againſt this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I ſay this people; with whom he never ſpake, but of whom he hath ſpoken <hi>too much,</hi> may we trade with thoſe of <hi>Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut,</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115072:35"/>who worſhip the Divel, and may we not admit of <hi>Iews</hi> who acknowledge and worſhip God? may we exerciſe trade with ſuch as deride and vilifie the mercies of Chriſt, and deny him, and may we not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them amongſt us to whom belong the promiſes? and to whom were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Oracles of God? ſhall we live amongſt Such who ſet up <hi>Idols,</hi> and ſhall we not imbrace thoſe that abhor them? May we, and do we trade with ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Popiſh Princes, and are with them in league for peace, or for war, and may we not bring in ſuch as deteſt the breach of Gods Commandments, and the <hi>Scarlet Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon?</hi> I ſay this, and ſay it again, <hi>that the vaile ſhall be taken away, and they ſhall ſee him</hi> (i. e.) by faith, <hi>whom they have pierced, and ſhall mourn bitterly,</hi> that is, they ſhall believe in Chriſt, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> and be ſaved; <hi>they are cut off,</hi> 'tis true at preſent, but their time of grafting <hi>In</hi> is coming, they, <hi>the Jews, ſhall be graft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed In and On again,</hi> their being <hi>Out,</hi> brings us <hi>In;</hi> it is Gods will that they ſhall be brought <hi>In,</hi> as Chriſt is the <hi>Light to the Gentiles, ſo he is the glory of the people Iſrael: Zachariah</hi> in his Song magnifies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115072:36"/>God for <hi>viſiting and redeeming his people;</hi> viſiting there is in <hi>love,</hi> and redeeming is in mercy; God loves them, and ſhall we hate them? the time will come when it ſhall be ſaid by of the <hi>Jews, I have ſeen, I have ſeen the affliction of my people</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd and diſperſt, I will come and deliver them; and my prayer is that of <hi>Davids, Redeeme Iſrael, (O God) out of all his troubles.</hi> I ſhut up all, and draw towards a concluſion, a ſtep or two further, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their admittance into <hi>England,</hi> we may do it.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115072:36"/>
            <p>7. <hi>From Civil Policy; and therein:</hi> 1. <hi>We being now a Free State.</hi> 2. <hi>To aboliſh the Edicts of Popiſh Kings of this Land againſt them:</hi> 3. <hi>From the great good that may come by it, not only of wealth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A well built houſe as it ought to have a good foundation, ſo alſo Pillars to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it, for certain 'tis, that as <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> are the fureſt foundation for to ground a <hi>State</hi> upon, ſo is <hi>Civil Policy, Wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> the beſt <hi>ſupporters</hi> of it: A great <hi>State,</hi> or potent Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is but the greater <hi>family,</hi> good counſel at home, guides and ſteers it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and firm in all hazards and tempeſts; and though not long ſince our preſent State by want of <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Councel</hi> was almoſt brought to ruine, and for certain was in a tottering condition; yet (praiſed be God) by <hi>prudent Councellors,</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> 'tis reedified, beautified, and ſtands <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115072:37"/>and <hi>internally</hi> glorious and renown'd, and is well recovered from a deſperate <hi>Feaver,</hi> a lingring <hi>Conſumption,</hi> a threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened <hi>ſlavery,</hi> and from deadly <hi>deſtruction,</hi> to health, vigour, and ſoundneſſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable liberty, nay even to <hi>life</hi> and <hi>well-being.</hi> The old foundations were decayed, and the <hi>Pillars</hi> were rotten, but (in Gods good providence) both removed, and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> more durable, being better ſeaſoned with <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>wiſdome,</hi> are ſet up and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced; and thou (O God) who of thy mercy didſt raiſe them for our good, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them as thy Builders, <hi>and Repairers of the old Breaches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come cloſe to our ſeventh Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for certain 'tis, that our ſlavery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Chriſtian and <hi>Civil Policy</hi> chang'd into liberty, and we rendred a <hi>Free Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> have we not power to relieve the <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> to ſupport the <hi>weak?</hi> have we not power to <hi>open</hi> or <hi>ſhut</hi> our doors, to whom we ſee it fitting and juſt? cannot we upon juſt grounds admit whom we pleaſe into our <hi>Society</hi> and <hi>friendſhip,</hi> and upon demerits or abuſes keep out or expel? Caunot we decree and determine with whom to trade and traffique, and whom to debar? may
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115072:37"/>not we raiſe up an <hi>ancient</hi> Family to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which hath been long caſt down, and who can juſtly blame or bark at our <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi> Seeing our <hi>intents</hi> are noble, the people whom we look on juſtly to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, and Gods hand moving in it for the <hi>augmentation of his glory,</hi> the filling up and compleating <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>myſtical</hi> Body; the <hi>gracing</hi> our Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and <hi>fulfilling</hi> Gods purpoſes and the <hi>Scriptures</hi> too, who but infatuated and malicious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits will contradict it?</p>
            <p>Add to theſe, and theſe are weighty things to be conſidered, the abundance of wealth, the flouriſhing of Trade, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of love, the reſtoring and repairing of old Breaches, the pouring in Oyl to an old wound; for their own ſakes too, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of what a <hi>royal, holy</hi> Off-ſpring and Generation they are, what a flouriſhing and indeed miraculous people they have been, who had God for their immediate Guide, by day and by night; whoſe Leaders have ſpoken often with God, whom God fed with Bread from Heaven fourty years, a people choſen out by God himſelf from and before all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115072:38"/>conſidering what a people they are at preſent, having neither Countrey, nor Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Houſe of their own; and yet have by Gods conduct (and certain it muſt needs be ſo) by Gods conduct, I ſay, ſubſiſted) in ſo many changes and alterations of places; and thoſe ſtrange Ones too, wanting Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and 'tis wonderfull how they got it, and <hi>Bread</hi> too, to uphold their fainting and hungry ſouls for ſixteen hundred years; which could never have been, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept God had been with them: add a little further (for my bowels do earn within me for this people) what a glorious, renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people they ſhall be, when grafted and joyned to <hi>our</hi> and <hi>their</hi> own Head <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that ſhall be; and even for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s, <hi>Iſaak</hi>'s, and <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſakes, their famous and never to be forgotten fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, once more for their large <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges,</hi> for the <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to them, for the <hi>Covenant,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his fleſh is <hi>bone</hi> of their <hi>bone,</hi> not aſhamed to call them <hi>Brethren.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lv, even for the <hi>Election</hi> ſake, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath it, <hi>by which they are beloved of the Father,</hi> for Gods <hi>Election</hi> (I ſay) of theſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115072:38"/>unto his Kingdom of grace here, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter, let their Requeſts come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Governours, and God more their hearts to entertain this people of God amongſt us, and let thy will O God be done in moving our Governours hearts to this end.</p>
            <p>And who but envious, ignorant, and uncharitable men will fret at it, or ſtrive to hinder ſo pious, ſo noble, ſo renowned, ſo gracious an Act: two things, I ſay, to theſe kinde of men, Suppoſe it ſhould ſo pleaſe God that they ſhould be expelled houſe and home, from kinred and all rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (and for certain it hath been ſo with ſome of them) would they not, nay did they not deſire pity and relief in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and why not the ſame to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> in their low ſtate and condition? The ſecond, May it not ſo come to paſs that ſome of them who are at preſent well ſeated, and ſettled, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all abundance, may not by ſome power be moved or removed? Or if not themſelves, may not ſome of their Loyns have their flittings and wandrings, and perhaps juſtly too? Would they not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115072:39"/>think it hard dealing, when as they ſhould come to the gates of a City, to be rail'd at, written againſt by invective Pens, faults laid to their charge great, and perhaps more than they were guilty of, onely to render them odious to the people that live therein; to be held as the peſts and Plagues, and if admitted will overthrow all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all, that they are accurſed, hated of God, and utterly forſaken for their ſins and groſs impieties; Would they deſire to be ſo uſed or abuſed? to have miſery added to their ſufferings, and would they that no pity, remorſe, compaſſion or relief ſhould be affor ded them, nor no Houſe, nor City, nor Countrey to give them entertainment? If they would not be ſo dealt withall them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, why do they yet ſo haſtily deal ſo with others that are in diſtreſs? Why ſo furious againſt Gods own Heritage, Gods own peculiar People, againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Branches? Becauſe it pleaſes God to puniſh them for a while, will theſe men make themſelves <hi>Executioners?</hi> O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the time was, when they would have taken it ill. But why do I wonder at the unchriſtian railing againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> when
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115072:39"/>as their Pen and Tougue ſcarce can ſpare any <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> I have finiſhed the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the <hi>Jews</hi> Admiſſion amongſt us. I now come to anſwer the Objections made againſt them, and they are four.</p>
            <div type="objections">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115072:40"/>
               <head>Four Objections againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> coming in anſwered.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>They will infect us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>They will infeſt us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>They are dangerous.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>They are ſcandalous.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Turbulent Spirits are like <hi>Clouds</hi> fill'd with <hi>Thunder,</hi> never will leave ſwelling bigger and blacker, till they burſt out, and aſunder, and then we have fair Sun-ſhine weather: ſurely the party who writ ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> coming <hi>in,</hi> was afraid <hi>his</hi> chamber in <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> ſhould have been for their habitation, or elſe his <hi>Mannour</hi> of <hi>Swainſcomb</hi> or <hi>Swainſwick,</hi> of which he writes himſelf <hi>Eſquire,</hi> but there is ſomthing of the <hi>Swainſ-Comb</hi> too in it; what, does he now want imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to plead at the <hi>Bar,</hi> or the <hi>Bench,</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and ſo pleads <hi>(being ſet on)</hi> ſo violently againſt the <hi>Jews?</hi> what will he leave no ſtone unmoved? it would have been thought a better work, and of more neceſſity, if he proved <hi>Bencher</hi> or <hi>Barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> againſt hmſelf, and paſt ſentence upon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115072:40"/>his <hi>own</hi> virulencies, <hi>Sed panci cupiunt in ſe deſcendere,</hi> the Preſs muſt render his fame and name in <hi>print</hi> come what will, this one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hint him a little.</p>
               <p>If it had not bin for ſuch unquiet ſpirits, the objections would not have been <hi>moot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but they ſhall be anſwered, and ſo to the firſt, concerning infection, if it be meant of their <hi>perſons,</hi> they are healthy, ſound, and perfect; and ſo no fear from them: if it be meant of their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> they came not in to teach, but to be taught; and what a ſtrange fear is that, that the <hi>Diſciple</hi> ſhould <hi>infect</hi> his <hi>Teacher, Doctrines,</hi> not taught, nor broach'd, nor vented; how can they be known to be infectious? neither can they, indeed be ſo, till vented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: poyſon lockt up, up in a box, kils not: but ſee what an eſteem they are made of, as a plague; but ſure, ſhould they prove ſuch, yet theſe are ſo ſound in the faith, that they ſure are out of danger; and for others they ſhall not be forced to give account.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond, concerning their infeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us who makes more trouble than theſe do? and yet they complain againſt theſe; But have we no Magiſtiate, or no Laws,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115072:41"/>or have theſe people no conſciences, they come in to be ſheltred and protected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from moleſtation and troubles; and will they beg in that here for which they fled for quiet, and peaceble dwelling; what hopes of prevailing; what ſhould they get? nay, what ſhould they not loſe? they bring in ſuch conſiderable eſtates that ſure they will have more wit than to loſe all, and themſelves too for an idle quarrel, ſurely if the Laws ſhould not, yet the ſouldier I beleive would quickly know a way, to turn ſuch buſie bodies hence well pillaged for melding in other mens matters, without Cauſe; ſo that alſo being an objection more of fear than truth, I paſs it over.</p>
               <p>To the third, for matter of danger in their admitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce, why more here than in other <hi>Countreys?</hi> if it be their <hi>multitude,</hi> a las! there's no Armies of them, neither are they that come in, if yet they do come in men of the Sword; and ſure there may be proviſion made for diſabling them to riſe as well as for the <hi>Cavalier,</hi> neither have they any Parties, <hi>Allies,</hi> Confederates; nay, but a few, if any friends to engage for them; what is it? in matter of trade they will be dangerous, they will quicken it,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115072:41"/>highten, augment, advance it, and enrich it: but have they any <hi>Ships</hi> of <hi>tranſportation</hi> to <hi>Countreys</hi> to ſend wealth to; where can they lay it <hi>ſafe?</hi> Sure they bring none, nor I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licve ſhall uſe any but what they hire of our Merchants, and they were never good <hi>Seamen,</hi> ſo that they muſt truſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> men with all; but perhaps they think <hi>victualls</hi> will be dearer, then money will be the more plentifull; and for ought I know upon an <hi>Exigent</hi> (they may by our <hi>courteous</hi> carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to them) eaſe a main part of the <hi>Taxes;</hi> and as it was ſaid before, How does <hi>Turkie</hi> abound in all ſorts of proviſions, notwithſtanding all the <hi>Jews</hi> throughout the <hi>Emperors</hi> Dominions? and therefore the danger is blown over, it is onely in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit not in reality.</p>
               <p>To the fourth, and of it bre fly conceru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Scandal;</hi> and how comes our elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be now <hi>ſcandalous?</hi> Accuſe him not <hi>unjuſtly, Scandall</hi> is either given or taken, if we give it, the fault is <hi>ours,</hi> if <hi>they,</hi> it muſt firſt be taken before it can be <hi>ſo,</hi> and then ſurely it muſt be <hi>firſt</hi> acted and reacted; which if it be, it muſt be either in <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>life,</hi> or both; for the firſt, it is notidetermined, onely imagined; they ſhall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115072:42"/>exerciſe their <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites; which yet is not <hi>granted,</hi> however there's room enough for us not to come <hi>near,</hi> and yet we may, and perhaps not be <hi>ſcandalized</hi> neither; he that will run into the fire, if he burn the fault's his own; if for life, ſurely the men are generally addicted to <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> obſerving ſtrictly the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, they are not given to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs nor riot nor pride, <hi>Content</hi> with ſpare diet, mean apparel, and lodging; they are rather indeed to be blamed for too much auſterity and ſtrickneſs in <hi>life,</hi> I rather think they will <hi>convince</hi> our looſe living, than any wiſe give occaſion of <hi>ſcandal</hi> to us; they are no <hi>gadders</hi> abroad, nor <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern-hunters,</hi> nor addicted to <hi>ſwearing,</hi> or <hi>curſing, ſtealing,</hi> or the like; but live <hi>civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> minding their <hi>occaſions,</hi> carrying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>ſtrictly</hi> towards the <hi>outward</hi> man: and where's this great <hi>Bug-Bear</hi> run, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Scandal?</hi> I wiſh we may not give them any, which is moſt to be feared.</p>
               <p>The people are <hi>witty, wiſe, ingenious, well-bred,</hi> addicted to <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>neat Arts</hi> and <hi>Inventions,</hi> pleaſing themſelves in a <hi>ſolitary retiredneſs;</hi> and what <hi>Scandal</hi> is herein? I have done with the two main
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115072:42"/>things. I propoſed to aſſert, and I leave my ſelf to the judgment of <hi>wiſe, moderate, just,</hi> and <hi>real Chriſtians,</hi> and God grant we may all (all, I ſay) as well <hi>Christians</hi> as <hi>Jews,</hi> forget the things <hi>that are behinde, and to preſs forwards towards the mark for the price of the high calling in</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, that all of us would <hi>ſtudy to live quiet, and to prevoke one another to good works, knowing that our labours ſhall not be in vain in the Lord. Amen. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſalm 132.13. <hi>For the Lord hath choſen</hi> Sion, <hi>and hath deſired it for his habitation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſe 17. <hi>There will I make the horn of</hi> David <hi>to bud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>So that her Saints ſhall ſing for joy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115072:43"/>
               <head>A just Vindication of Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> from the virulent and unjust Accuſation of Mr. <hi>William Prynn</hi> Bencher of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colns</hi> Inn.</head>
               <p>OUr Saviour ſpeaks it, that <hi>out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh,</hi> Surely, this ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Scribe doth ſhew that he is ſtuff'd full of paſſion and malice, becauſe he vents ſo much; He is not onely bitter but ſuperlative invective againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> but he drives as furiouſly againſt his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Countreymen, and as he is unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould come In; ſo he would be as much pleaſed if ſome of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men were turn'd Out, and though he is never fit to be a Judg, yet what he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairs to enjoy, he doth aſſume and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to Judg and cenſure others from his ſtudy and Chamber, and truly moſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; how little he intends, our bleſſed Lords words appears ſufficiently, Judg not that ye be not judged: Or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, what art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant, and ſure he approves not the Prophet <hi>David</hi>'s ſpeech, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. Thou
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115072:43"/>ſateſt and ſpakeſt againſt thy brother: If this Eſquire did but ſeriouſly think and conſider that we <hi>muſt give an account for every idle word,</hi> ſurely he would not multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vain words ſo as he does to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and if in a multitude of words there is ſin, certain it is that he cannot be free, it's to be wiſhed he would remember, that by his words he ſhall be juſtified, and by his words he ſhall be condemned: and if an ELDER be not to be rebuked, much leſs is he to be reviled; the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſays concerning falſe tongues, that GOD will pull them out of their dwelling, then it's high time for this party to have a better care of his tongue than he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had of his Ears; the one procured the Ruin of the other, &amp; though he thinks that LOOSERS may ſpeak; yet not what they liſt, or againſt whom they luſt; except he intends to do as they did in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. <hi>We will ſpeak, our tongues are our own, and who is Lord over us?</hi> but I could adviſe the man to remember well what the Prophet <hi>David</hi>'s practiſe was, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. I ſaid I will take heed unto my ways that I offend not with my tongue; I will keep my mouth as it were with a Bit and a Bridle, and <hi>Solomon</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115072:44"/>us to ponder our words, and it's great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſuſpected that Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> doth not much regard his words becauſe he laviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them ſo away; Well, becauſe oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious language is like a Gangreen that ſpreads and infects others, and becauſe thoſe that are written peiree the deeper and endure the longer as being (to uſe the phraſe of this Scribe) upon Record, and as he urges, Records are not to be meddled withall; I think it fitting to apply a ſe aſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able but a ſhort Reply to this man in his higheſt carreir and to tell him how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, unreaſonably, and unconſcionably, againſt the Rules of modeſty, prudence, equity, and Chriſtianity too, he hath in the vilifying not onely the <hi>Jews,</hi> but alſo his own brethren and fathers trangreſſed, and that firſt;</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath lived in and practiſed this ſin of Rayling and Reviling, and evil ſpeaking and writing for many years, the longer any lives in, and practiſeth his ſin, the worſe ſtate and condition he muſt be in; and who knows not if he know any thing, but that <hi>W. P. Eſq;</hi> hath vented his ſpleen and gaul and bitterneſs of ſpirit, for many indeed for too many years,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115072:44"/>though not without publick and ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the very deteſtable nature of the crime, being proh ibited by God and man, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bring a railing Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And it's no good thing to accuſe, but to accuſe and rail, O 'tis injurious in a high degree, <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Shimei</hi>'s his railing would not puniſh him himſelf, but refers him to Gods juſtice, yet though he did not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, lay and inflict vengeance upon him, yet he puts it into the hands of <hi>Solomon</hi> to execute, and adviſes him not to let his gray hairs go in peace to the grave, but bids him remember. By all means to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that notorious fact of the Miſcreant, and <hi>Solomon</hi> forgot it not, but acted wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolidly in the matter, and when time ſerv'd tels him home of it; thou knoweſt (ſays he) the wickedneſs of thy heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and lays the guilt of his own bloud upon his own head: O! it's a dangerous infeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and infecting evil; Conſider well of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He acting it againſt perſons no ways meriting it at his hands, O! ſays <hi>James,</hi> the tongue is ſet on fire, and it burns to Hell, it's an unruly evil; who can tame it? but it's then worſe when it opens againſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115072:45"/>an innocent; ſurely, it's no ways lawfull or juſtifiable to wound and gaſh our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, freind; or brethren, much leſs our Fathers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How ſlandring, railing, and reviling ſtirs up Contention, diſgraces the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity; makes our good to be evil ſpoken of, gives offence and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall to them that are weak, argues corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of heart, makes men the ſons of the Devil; leaves a deep tincture of ſtrife and debate, if not blacker and uglier miſchiefs, is clean contrary to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s practiſe, who when he was reviled, reviled not again.</p>
               <p>But he ſays and urges againſt this our Father of our Church and Champion of our reformed Religion two things, the firſt is an Act, the ſecond is for Words, But ſure upon examination we ſhall finde that neither the Action nor the Words of him can juſtly merit ſo long and ſo deep a brand of ignominy and diſparagement as this our teſty and waſpiſh Penman hath rendred both of them to the world.</p>
               <p>To begin, therefore firſt come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rning the act charged upon him; an act if the Lawyer might have his will ſhould be Actionable, if not Treaſonable too; for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115072:45"/>he came with a Sword of Steel under his Arm, inſtead of the Sword of the Spirit. Well, and what followed? Carried my ſelf and many other worthy Members of the Nation into Hell, and kept us, (as he ſays) and it is but his ſay ſo, there upon the hard ſtones all night: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was well that he did come, yet not without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and commiſſion, which was juſt and warrantable from the Lord General; but he came with a Sword; if he had done ſo, it had been but what he might do, and what at that time was but neceſſary; Why may not a ſpiritual man wear a Sword? What not upon a journey or ſome great imployment, and this was no other? had not our Saviours own Apoſtles ſome Swords amongſt them? yet were not condemned for carrying them, nor for ſtriking neither, if they had had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for it; <hi>Samuel</hi> was a ſpiritual man, yet call'd for a Sword, and uſed it ſeverely too, the hewing <hi>Agag</hi> in peices, yet the act is nor condemned, or cen ſured for unjuſt; no not that valorous act of <hi>Phinees</hi> before him, but was ſo far from being unlawfull that it is commended for righteous to all generations.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115072:46"/>
               <p>And if he had come arm'd, it might have been juſtified, but he did not, but came alone to ſpeak with two members of the Houſe, and to uſe his own expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 'twas in the night and without a Sword, and Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> with others was then in the Queens Lodgings and not in Hell: and 'twas ſtrange that being in Hell they ſhould be a cold, he knows who it was, being in Hell, cryed out that he was <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in that flame;</hi> and it ſeems as ſtrange too, that Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of his being almoſt ſterved; and yet he was in a <hi>Cooks ſhop,</hi> but had he been truly in Hell, he could never have procured a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to get out again;</p>
               <p>But why does the man of the long Robe exclaim ſo bitterly againſt him? did he give him any wounds, or did he threaten him, or force any uncivil Action upon him? If none of theſe, why ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling and indeed ſlandering of an abſent and innocent perſon? But the perſon is hated for his calling, for being one that hath ſo long by doing and ſuffering for the truth and contending by many (I ſay) tentations at home, and abroad for the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115072:46"/>faith; yet holds out and is ſound, and entire to his profeſſion of the Goſpel; if any can ſay, and apply that place of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> he may to himſelf; for he hath been in perils at Sea, in perils at Land, in perils amongſt falſe brethren, in hunger and cold, in famine and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in perils in the Wilderneſs, in perils amongſt his own countreymen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this for his conſtant adhering to, and loving the ſincerity of the Goſpel; but I adviſe Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> to take heed how he wrongs the leaſt of theſe little Ones, 'tis hard to kick againſt the pricks, but more ſpecially not to cauſe his own Tongue and Pen to accuſe and condemn himſelf, for ſlandering the upright in heart: Nor as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith to cauſe his fleſh to ſin. That's for ſatisfaction for the Acts, had it been done as Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> reports it.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond thing that inflames his ſpirit ſo to rage and rant it <hi>ad randum in folio,</hi> is (as he ſays) that Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> ſhould deſire and would have all the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Records of the Nation to be burn'd, and that makes him beſtir himſelf for fear leaſt the common Law Records ſhould be included in the Number; To this we ſay,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115072:47"/>and truly it is the ſafeſt way of anſwering him by, the Gentlemans own words, out of his printed book which yet was but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for ſome private papers paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and a freind, and not ſo much intended for publick, though indeed they are of publick uſe and benefit; and fit to be practiſed in a well govern'd and Chriſtian Common wealth; but ſure there is no ſuch poyſon in them as this Spider hath ſuck'd from them; at <hi>folio</hi> 33. of his book cal'd good work for a good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, he ſaith,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That if the Premiſes were carried on,</hi> viz. <hi>of the Law truly reformed, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters in every Pariſh whereby every man may know, and enjoy his own whileſt he lives, and be ſure his will ſhould be performed when he is dead; It were beſt all Records that lie any where to hinder ſuch a ſettlement were bur'nd, yea, the Records in the</hi> Tower, <hi>that are the Monuments of Tyranny, for mark what he Mr.</hi> Prynn <hi>writes,</hi> Relatio fit ad proximum antecedens, <hi>and then ſure he looſeth his aim; for let the things be ſcand throughly and there is no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as he is ſo ſtartled at; for look at the matter going before, and that was</hi> the Law
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115072:47"/>regulated. <hi>How? the</hi> Exorbitancies <hi>of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Fees, of injurious D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emurs, of</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Offices, <hi>and unfit perſons in them, with thouſands beſides theſe, 'tis this is the</hi> ſtone of offence, and ſo perplexes the pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Gentleman; yet whether this be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be done, we leave to all honeſt heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to judg.</p>
               <p>And yet now we are upon it; one word or two to the very Law, the common Law it ſelf honoured and indeed idolized by Mr. <hi>Prynn;</hi> I hope he will not ſay it is like that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unalterable, it was impos'd not for the good, but the curb of this Nation, by the <hi>Norman</hi> Tyrant; and why may not another generation finde out as good or better Principles to govern by, as that? and as wiſe, and as faithfull Lawyers to manage it? Was the Law and the Sword too tied onely to his head-peice? We know the very conſtitution of men in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ages do differ? And what might then be known to be neceſſary for that time and generation of men? Muſt it needs be ſo, alſo now, and of force binding for the <hi>future?</hi> Becauſe there ſtands an old Houſe built by the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> may it not be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115072:48"/>
                  <hi>altered,</hi> or if this age thinks and findes it fitting; utterly pull'd down? though the Law doth bridle, and puniſh many haynous and capital crimes <hi>juſtly,</hi> and keeps us from living like <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Bears,</hi> yet the Law as now practis'd, and managed by <hi>ſome Officers,</hi> I will not ſay <hi>Barreſters,</hi> and <hi>Benchers</hi> too; yet they are ſcarce excuſable, the Law is made but as a ſtalking horſe for gain, let any man ſeriouſly conſider but theſe three things, which are ſtrange and ſad to think upon in the Law; and then let him tell the excellent neceſſity, and profit of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let them conſider how moſt men go and get into the Law; into it I ſay. with what <hi>vaſt</hi> charge, I of Moneys and time, with malice to boot; the charge ſometimes exceeding the main ſuit it ſelf, and reducing a mans eſtate to <hi>Atomes:</hi> and the malice extending to two or three generations, if not more to the diſgrace of Chriſtianity, beſides the journeys in Winter and Summer, with charg of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How it is managed when a man is in: with all <hi>ſubtilty, policy, contrivances,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115072:48"/>ſearching, plotting, undermining; tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> with Witneſſes: ſtretching the ſenſe of the Law on the <hi>tenter-hooks,</hi> ſearching old rotten <hi>Records,</hi> to cull out any thing that may ſerve to advantage the Lawyers Purſes, continuation of the Suit, and then on the Defendants ſide what <hi>Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges?</hi> what Pretences? what Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? what <hi>Demurs?</hi> On the other ſide, what haſte for <hi>Proceſs,</hi> for <hi>Writs, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, Arreſts, Judgments, Executions, Extents,</hi> and <hi>Exigents, Reſtringas, Fieri facias,</hi> and <hi>Capias utlegatum,</hi> and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſuch vexatious courſes, and all grounded upon a falſe <hi>information,</hi> or ſome little Treſpaſs at firſt?</p>
               <p n="3">3. How to get <hi>out</hi> when once <hi>in,</hi> hopes, and <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>moneys,</hi> and able <hi>Lawyers</hi> counſel and advice, and encouragement too, are as ſo many <hi>Engines</hi> to attract and draw in <hi>Game,</hi> with deſire of <hi>Revenge,</hi> and to have the credit of the <hi>Day,</hi> and that they cry all's their <hi>own,</hi> not to leave his Adverſary worth a <hi>Groat,</hi> and the like: and add to theſe the <hi>ſubtilty</hi> of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, who <hi>promiſe</hi> fair, pretend care and diſpatch, ſecrecy, and the procuration of helps at laſt by ſome old <hi>quirk</hi> and <hi>quillet,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115072:49"/>though for nothing elſe but to keep his Client <hi>in,</hi> till he is forced <hi>out,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>outlawed</hi> or law'd <hi>out</hi> of all his Eſtate.</p>
               <p>I end this with a ſhort but a true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Charges of going to Law; It was ſhewed to a <hi>Committee</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> of 60. of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> that paſt for 2. <hi>s.</hi> for the whole Conveyance of Houſe and Lands worth 3000. <hi>l.</hi> and at the ſame time 55. ſheets of of Paper ſhewn for the Conveyance but of 1500. <hi>l.</hi> and coſt 50. <hi>l.</hi> a vaſt difference betwixt 2. <hi>s.</hi> for 300. <hi>l.</hi> and 50. <hi>l.</hi> for but 1500. <hi>l.</hi> and yet the <hi>Law</hi> nor <hi>Lawyers</hi> would be thought to be <hi>chargeable</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</hi> But this by digreſſion, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> condemns him generally; but let him but reviſe the whole, and then ſure all will be allowable: For firſt, he would have thoſe <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes carried on. Secondly, he would have the Law not <hi>annihilated,</hi> but truly <hi>regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Thirdly, he would have <hi>Regiſters</hi> in every <hi>Pariſh</hi> firſt ſettled, not done <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> hand over head. Fourthly, he would have every man <hi>know</hi> his Eſtate, <hi>enjoy</hi> it, and be <hi>aſſured</hi> of the performance of his
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115072:49"/>
                  <hi>will.</hi> Fifthly, he does not ſay <hi>all</hi> Records ſimply, but all <hi>ſuch</hi> Records as do hinder <hi>that</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſettlement.</hi> Sixthly, nor all in general, but ſuch as are <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,</hi> and oppreſſion, and of ſlavery; and what matters it whether they ly in the <hi>Tower,</hi> or elſewhere? Now why is this Gentleman ſo far tranſported, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ſatisfie him, but as much as in him lies to diſgrace, to vilifie, to rail at, and revile this painfull <hi>Patriot,</hi> for his wiſe and judicious <hi>modeling</hi> and endeavouring to reform that which ſtands in high need of it.</p>
               <p>But how would he have had matter to have ſo inveigh'd againſt the noble Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> had not he been furniſh'd with the <hi>old Records</hi> (as he calls them) of <hi>Friers</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Legends</hi> to make his Book to ſwell? beſides the large Privileges and gains he hath perhaps made by poring into them, to help to <hi>lengthen</hi> and <hi>prolong</hi> a Suit in Law, tedious enough of it ſelf, and therefore would not have his <hi>Supporters</hi> ſuppreſſed or removed? Add hereunto the <hi>fond</hi> humour the Gentleman hath to grace his Books, and to credit himſelf, to ſhew how ſtudious he is, and how voluminous
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115072:50"/>his <hi>Library,</hi> beſide to perſwade men that's <hi>all</hi> true which he writes, atteſted with ſuch <hi>unlegible</hi> Marginals of antiquated <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authours, not to be approved of in other caſes, but the <hi>onely</hi> Champions he uſes in <hi>this;</hi> But why may not we entertain ſome <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>England?</hi> when as <hi>Venice</hi> alone entertains eighty thouſand of them, and <hi>Rome</hi> no leſs than one hundred and fifty thouſand, without any offence, or trouble, or charge, but contrariwiſe with a great deal of advantage, and certain gain and profit.</p>
               <p>But to conclude all, we and ſo any one that's but eaſily read in <hi>Politicks</hi> may finde out the cauſe of Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s diſtempered Accuſation againſt his <hi>own</hi> Brother, a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, painfull, ſolid, and ſincere, orthodox Preacher of Gods Word: ſeldom does any man love thoſe that <hi>ſeem</hi> to ſtop or hinder a mans <hi>Reputation</hi> or <hi>Gains,</hi> wee'll put both <hi>in.</hi> Now Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> was a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Parliament, and to be debarr'd ſitting any longer (though they ſate too long) amongſt others, was a ſeeming ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to his <hi>credit,</hi> and a ſure ſtop to his profit and gains, to loſe both theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unexpectedly cuts deep: and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115072:50"/>having no need of him for further imploiment, having nothing elſe to do, he ſhews you what he would do, if his <hi>power</hi> was proportionable to his <hi>will:</hi> and becauſe he cannot <hi>bite</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he doth injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and unjuſtly <hi>bark</hi> at thoſe whom otherways he cannot reach or hurt; and we ſay, 'Twas no matter if all the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authours out of which he hath fetch'd his far-fetch'd and <hi>unprofitable</hi> quotations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and whoſe authority he ſo much relies upon, whether they be thoſe in his <hi>ſtudy</hi> or elſewhere if they were <hi>burn'd,</hi> we ſay <hi>burn'd,</hi> who have been the <hi>cauſers</hi> and procurers of ſuch troubles, and have had a hand in the <hi>burning</hi> of ſo many of Gods people in this Land; for if their Calling be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> ſuperſtitious, and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian;</hi> what hopes are there that their works ſhould be other? Either make the Tree good and his Fruit good, or the Tree bad and the Fruit bad; <hi>A bad Tree cannot bring forth good Fruit; Do men gather</hi> (ſays our Saviour) <hi>Grapes of Thorns or Figs of Thistles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſhut up all, I found a great deal of hard meaſure uſed towards the <hi>Jews,</hi> but by none ſo much as by Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s Pen;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115072:51"/>I have done the beſt I could to clear the foul <hi>Imputations</hi> and <hi>Aspertions</hi> laid upon them; I deſire all who ſhall reade the Book to lay aſide all prejudicacy of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to conſider the buſineſs not as it is made to be, but as indeed it is, and ſo leave the iſſue to <hi>Gods</hi> time and good pleaſure, to whoſe protection I commend all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and ſincere <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in whom is no guile.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, I could deſire that the ſaid Gentleman would ſeriouſly bethink him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf what a ſin it is to blot and blemiſh a <hi>Man,</hi> an <hi>Elder</hi> in his good name, and to force and lay things to his charge that he never did ſpeak or write, but to corrupt and pervert his words; for certain 'tis a deep fault; an ingenious <hi>Recantation</hi> or <hi>Retractation</hi> would be no <hi>derogation</hi> to him, and would ſhew a ſpirit of meekneſs, fobriety, and ingenuity, and evidence a conſcience willing to render <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and would be a ready way to work a fair and ſure <hi>Reconciliation</hi> both with God and Man, which how fitting and neceſſary this is to be done, is left to his <hi>retired</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved</hi> conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="dedication">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115072:51"/>
               <head>To the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO you, who are <hi>despiſed,</hi> and the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts,</hi> and the <hi>off-ſcouring</hi> of the World in many, too many mens opinions; to you, who are adjudged of moſt not fit to be entertain'd into <hi>Society</hi> or <hi>conference,</hi> are theſe few lines directed and dedicated, who though <hi>ſoiled</hi> and <hi>ſullied</hi> with a long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, may yet return to him that hath ſmitten you, and finde reſt, conſolation, and refreſhment to your ſouls and bodies, by the infinite mercy and love of God the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>You cannot but know that your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries are <hi>many,</hi> both for <hi>Tongue</hi> and <hi>Pen,</hi> you ſee <hi>few</hi> or none appearing to plead <hi>for you,</hi> yet amongſt thoſe few this Authour hath expoſed himſelf in your defence, he weighs not the reproaches of men, ſo he may do you good, and be ſerviceable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, for your gathering and grafting <hi>in</hi> again.</p>
               <p>Two things are offered to you; the firſt is of <hi>comfort,</hi> the ſecond is of <hi>direction,</hi> both <hi>neceſſary,</hi> that of comfort ſhall be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115072:52"/>firſt, becauſe you ſtand in <hi>moſt</hi> need of it, and <hi>few</hi> or <hi>none</hi> afford it to you.</p>
               <p>Know therefore that <hi>God hath not caſt away</hi> you <hi>his people,</hi> he that <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. ſaid <hi>I have ſeen, I have ſeen the affliction of my people that are in Egypt</hi> unto your noble Progenitors, ſees alſo all your affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions through the whole world.</p>
               <p>Gods Rod lay upon them 430. years in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and 70. years in the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> Captivity, yet he forgot not his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but did bring them out of both; and though this hath continued almoſt 4. times longer than the longeſt of them, yet a 1000. <hi>years are with the Lord but as one day,</hi> he will for certain, he will yet redeem and deliver you.</p>
               <p>And therefore <hi>lift up your heads, for the time</hi> of <hi>your Redemption draweth nigh, yet a little while and he that ſhall come will come and not tarry,</hi> with healing in his wings; <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, know what a change you ſhall partake of; <hi>beauty</hi> for <hi>aſhes,</hi> joy for <hi>mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the <hi>Garments</hi> of <hi>gladneſs</hi> for the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>ſadneſs,</hi> he will gather up his <hi>Jewels,</hi> and you that have been <hi>toſt,</hi> and given for <hi>loſt,</hi> will he imbrace and honour
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115072:52"/>and Crown with everlaſting love and glory?</p>
               <p>To ſtir up and kindle mens <hi>affections</hi> to regard you and ſhew <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to you, and to keep up your <hi>ſpirits</hi> from fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to wait upon <hi>God;</hi> I manifeſt four things tending to your glory, the firſt is your noble <hi>Pedigree</hi> and extraction. The ſecond, your honourable <hi>Titles.</hi> Thirdly, your eminent <hi>Prerogatives.</hi> And fourthly, your exceeding <hi>Priviledges:</hi> of each ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for your extraction and <hi>pedigree,</hi> you have been ſtudious to ſearch about <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogies,</hi> now according to the Scriptures, your <hi>Original</hi> is from the firſt of Men, this is evident in the firſt of <hi>Chron.</hi> the nine firſt Chapters, and ſo in <hi>Luke</hi> 3. from the 23 verſ. bringing your deſcent even to him who was the <hi>joy of the whole earth,</hi> and <hi>the Glory of Iſrael,</hi> from whom you had the <hi>trueſt, higheſt,</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> Nobility that ever was given to men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for your <hi>Titles, illuſtrious</hi> and <hi>ſtupendious.</hi> Called <hi>Hebrews</hi> from <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> Son of <hi>Salah Noahs</hi> grandchilde, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.14. which name ſignifies <hi>paſſage</hi> or in a <hi>paſſive ſignification, paſſing paſſage,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115072:53"/>you being as it were an <hi>Intermedium</hi> for the <hi>conveyance of Grace,</hi> God giving <hi>you</hi> his <hi>Ordinances</hi> to receive as it were by the <hi>firſt</hi> hand, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by a <hi>ſecond; Actively</hi> taken, you were <hi>more near</hi> God in your ſervices; and therefore, <hi>ſurpaſſing</hi> in the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>purity</hi> of your <hi>Religious</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true, pure, and <hi>everlaſting</hi> God. You are call'd <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> an name of <hi>Honour</hi> given by the <hi>Angel to Jacob, Gen.</hi> 23. v. 28. <hi>Prince</hi> of God, or <hi>Prevailer</hi> or <hi>Conqueror</hi> of God, who was a <hi>chief Patriarch</hi> of, and amongſt <hi>you,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing in <hi>prayers, ſacrifices,</hi> and <hi>ſervices;</hi> therefore are you ſtil'd commonly the <hi>Children of Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 33.1. And fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the <hi>people of Iſrael;</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſirous to ingratiate himſelf with you, for he cals you <hi>the Men of Iſrael. Acts</hi> 2.22. You are the people who properly are call'd a <hi>choſen Generation, a holy Prieſt-hood, a holy Nation, a peculiar people,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. you are call'd <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Judah, Jacob</hi>'s, fourth ſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.35. which ſignifieth praiſe, you being the praiſe of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet the Scripture gives you higher and more honourable Titles than theſe, more relating to the <hi>Deity,</hi> as <hi>his peculiar
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115072:53"/>treaſure</hi> Exod. 19.5. <hi>the people of the Lord,</hi> Deut. 29. the <hi>Lords Children.</hi> Deut. 14.1. <hi>his firſt-born,</hi> Exod. 4.22. <hi>his Inheritance.</hi> 1 Kings, 85.1. <hi>the Lot of his Inheritance. Jer.</hi> 10.16. you are call'd <hi>Gods Vineyard,</hi> Pſal. 80. Iſay 5.1. Jer. 2.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For your Prerogatives large and wonderfull indeed, God choſe you out of a people <hi>to be a choſen people to himſelf,</hi> Deut. 6.7. <hi>To make you high above all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth, in praiſe, and in Name, and in Honour,</hi> Deut. 26.19. He is ſaid to be <hi>more nigh to you than any Nation,</hi> Deut. 19.7. you received Gods word before any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation.</hi> Pſalm 104.19.20. <hi>In</hi> Judah <hi>is God known, his Name is great in Iſrael; in</hi> Salem or (Hieruſalem) was his <hi>Taberracle,</hi> and his dwelling in <hi>Syon;</hi> the mount whereon <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple ſtood, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1.2. And <hi>John,</hi> 4 22. unto you did <hi>Chriſt</hi> preach, called you <hi>Children</hi> the Gentiles <hi>Dogs; Chriſt</hi> would not let his <hi>diſciples</hi> preach the <hi>Gospel</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or to any Cities of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> till they had begun at <hi>Hieruſalem, Matth.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. Which precedency belong'd to you by right of Covenant, <hi>to you and to your ſeed, Acts</hi> 2.39.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115072:54"/>
               <p>Fourthly, for your <hi>Privileges,</hi> exceeding <hi>many</hi> and <hi>high ones,</hi> God himſelf will be known by this, <hi>I am the God of the</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.18. He promiſeth <hi>to ſet you on high above all Nations,</hi> ſhowring down all bleſſings upon you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1, 2. and <hi>to make you a Kingdom of Prieſts, and an holy Nation, Exod.</hi> 10.4, 6. Unto you did God <hi>commit his Oracles, Rom.</hi> 3.2. But above all, is that, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born of <hi>you,</hi> and made his <hi>firſt</hi> profers of <hi>grace</hi> and love to <hi>you;</hi> amongſt thoſe eight ſeveral <hi>Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> God beſtowed on you: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ends all in this, <hi>Who are</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>to whom ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth the Adoption, and Glory, and the Covenant, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the Promiſes, and of whom as concerning the fleſh</hi> Chriſt <hi>came, Rom.</hi> 9.4, 5. And when as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would defend his Apoſtleſhip, and keep up the <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of it, he uſeth Arguments from his <hi>Privileges,</hi> as he was a <hi>Jew, Are they</hi> Hebrews, <hi>ſo am I?</hi> Are they <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo am I? Are they of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo am I? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. accounting theſe <hi>Privileges</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt carnal bleſſings that were given unto men. To theſe add, that you were <hi>Holy
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115072:54"/>Brethren, Partakers of the heavenly Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Phil.</hi> 3.1. Of you it was that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke and thought <hi>ſuch things as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company ſalvation, becauſe of your work and labour of love,</hi> which you have ſhewed in miniſtring to the Saints, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.9, 10. Theſe are thoſe comfortable, honourable, and excellent Titles, Prerogatives, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, that are aſcribed unto you above all other Nations and People, and are high <hi>Incentives</hi> and deep <hi>Ingagements</hi> to make you walk <hi>worthy</hi> ſuch excellent <hi>Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and benefits, and to raiſe up your drooping <hi>ſpirits,</hi> even in the <hi>midst</hi> of all your long and deep <hi>Viſitation;</hi> for as the Prophet, <hi>Though you have layn among the Pots, yet ſhall ye be as the wings of a Dove covered with Silver, &amp;c. Pſalm</hi> 68.13. and God <hi>will bring again his own people, even as he did ſometimes from the depth of the Sea, Pſalm</hi> 68.22. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> beyond all mens help and expectation, with a mighty hand, and out-ſtretched Arm, and <hi>then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be glad,</hi> that for your comfort. The ſecond thing premiſed:</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is for your <hi>direction,</hi> and that ſhall be brief: Firſt, Hate and leave off that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115072:55"/>ſin which procured this your ſuffering by repentance, that your ſins may be blotted out when the time of your refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be inceſſant with God in Prayer, that he would be pleaſed to remember the time, the ſet time, to have mercy upon <hi>Sion,</hi> for it pitieth her Servants to ſee her in the duſt, and that he would open your eys, and give you underſtanding hearts to believe in and know him whom God hath ſent, <hi>Jeſus Christ, John</hi> 17.3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſearch the Scriptures, and in reading them, to pray God <hi>to take away the vail</hi> that is upon your hearts, for <hi>the Letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life.</hi> And conſider <hi>the Miniſtration of the Spirit is much more glorious than that of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>old things are paſſed away, and all things are become new,</hi> and that though <hi>the Law was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>yet grace and truth came by</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, John 1. and that now <hi>there is no difference betwixt</hi> Jew <hi>and</hi> Gentile, Barbarian <hi>or</hi> Scythian, <hi>bond or free, but we are all one in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whereſoever you ſhall come, to be carefull of your carriage, to give no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115072:55"/>but to walk worthy of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that high Calling in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude all, I have diſcharged my conſcience in your behalf; God is able to bring great things to paſs by ſmall Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though I be the leaſt, yet I am one that wiſh well to <hi>Sion</hi> and do heartily pray, that <hi>God would give you favour in the ſight of the Nations,</hi> and that all thoſe that keep you captives <hi>may pity you,</hi> and that the Nations ſeeing your converſion <hi>may glorifie God on your behalf,</hi> and ſay, <hi>What hath God done? This is the Lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it is marvellous in our eys.</hi> So be it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="cautions">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115072:56"/>
               <head>Certain Cautions concerning the <hi>Jews</hi> Admiſsion into <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not fit to <hi>direct,</hi> much leſs to <hi>preſcrthe</hi> to <hi>Superiours,</hi> in laying down theſe few Cautions neither is intended, onely to render ſome <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to ſuch who are the great and <hi>violent Oppoſers</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion amongſt us, who though they have no ſolid or ſubſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntial grounds for their Oppoſition at all, yet by theſe Cautions that may ſeem tolerable, if not allowable to their judgments, which before was held altogether unjuſt and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>And certain it is, that had Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> in his multitude of Scripture-quotations ſeriouſly conſidered that moſt, if not all theſe places, which mention either the ſins or the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this people related to the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115072:56"/>
                  <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, or to what of judgments, before that, God was pleaſed to inflict upon them, he would not have ſo injuriouſly brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one Generation for another, and make thoſe Curſes &amp; Plagues which are terminated in the third or fourth Generation of them that hate him, to be due to the thirteenth or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Generation downwards, and of them too who he knows not, whether they hate God or not.</p>
               <p>And ſo alſo for his almoſt innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable but unneceſſary Rabble of <hi>Popiſh</hi> antiquated Writers, Edicts, Statutes, Decrees, and Records; for theſe (I ſay) if he had conſidered that what was then (if yet it was then, for we may not give credit to all he ſays and quotes) is not Now, for <hi>Now</hi> is not <hi>Then,</hi> nor <hi>Then Now;</hi> he would (I believe) in modeſty have ſpared that needleſs ſearch, nor have ſo bin confident to pin his faith upon
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115072:57"/>thoſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Papers and worm-eaten Scriblers, who yet (as it is by wiſe men judged) writ out of malice, and the the Spirit of Lying too againſt the <hi>Jews;</hi> for how much credit is to be given to ſuch perſons who have not bluſhed to corrupt the ſacred Text it ſelf, and to adulterate all both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Fathers; for certain ſuch audacious Spirits would not ſpare (when their gains and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit lay at ſtake) and when it was in their power too) to lay load enough and the heavieſt always on the weakeſt ſhoulders, and ſuch was the people of the <hi>Jews</hi> in theſe times, to cauſe them to be odious to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>This mans great opinion of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Judgment hath tainted and poiſoned many mens affections, and hardened them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſolutely againſt the Admiſſion of any <hi>Jews</hi> amongſt us; when yet any one ſees how weak
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115072:57"/>his Arguments are, if well ſcann'd, and how little of truth is in them.</p>
               <p>To perſwade therefore the ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that what at firſt did ſeem alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>unfitting,</hi> upon ſecond and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>reflections</hi> ſhall be found not onely fitting but <hi>beneficial</hi> alſo, and what at <hi>firſt</hi> apprehenſion ſeem'd ſo full of danger, may upon <hi>review</hi> be found nothing ſo, I ſay, it is not our intendment, that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould come in, ſo as Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> ſeems to fear, <hi>to diſhonour God</hi> and <hi>Chrst Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſubvert <hi>Religion,</hi> diſturb the Laws, raiſe up Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſterve our own Countreymen and Natives, undo <hi>merchandizing,</hi> ſeduce the <hi>People,</hi> diſgrace the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, rob us of our Wealth, bring Gods <hi>Plagues, Curſes,</hi> and <hi>Judgments</hi> amongſt us, with many other ſuch terrible conceited <hi>Chymaeraes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No nor yet to come Ruſhing in, as an overflowing floud, to drown all
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115072:58"/>
                  <hi>Religion, Laws,</hi> and all our <hi>Privileges,</hi> nor yet to be ſuch <hi>Hors-leaches,</hi> and Spunges of out Treaſure, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it away; nor to uſurp upon any mans <hi>Birthright,</hi> nor yet to Cozen, oppreſs, poll, pill, defraud, fleece, and ſqueeze the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, nor yet to grinde them, or cheat them by <hi>uſury,</hi> fraud, or the like. Nor laſtly, to circumciſe or crucifie, any children in <hi>deriſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor to <hi>ſacrifices</hi> any <hi>Bulls,</hi> or <hi>Oxen,</hi> or <hi>Sheep,</hi> or <hi>Lambs;</hi> for that part of their Religion is too coſtly; and the other is too painfull; both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable: but for certain they may be admitted <hi>in</hi> upon divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, ſome of them are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the <hi>leave</hi> of the ſupreme <hi>Legis-lators</hi> of our <hi>Nation;</hi> they formerly have been, and may if when they pleaſe be again, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; and who can, or dare charge
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:115072:58"/>
                  <hi>their</hi> Actions for unjuſt? they haveing power to <hi>ſave,</hi> or <hi>deſtroy;</hi> and therefore, power to determine matters of leſs conſequence; and then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their admiſſion, being from <hi>them,</hi> and but <hi>Premiſsive,</hi> not <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> but <hi>quod diu ſe bene geſſerint,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſuch ſolid <hi>orders</hi> as by the <hi>Governours</hi> of our <hi>Nation</hi> ſhall be adjudged moſt <hi>convenient, juſteſt</hi> and moſt <hi>conducing</hi> to Gods glory, and ths Honor of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of our people.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That there <hi>chief heads,</hi> and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, do at their entrance or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after give in good ſecurity, for all that come in to live quietly, and ſubordinately, to our Laws, in all civil reſpects; ſo that <hi>juſtice,</hi> as well <hi>communitative,</hi> as <hi>diſtributive</hi> may have it's <hi>full</hi> vigour, as well to releive, ſuccour and defend <hi>them</hi> when <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> or moleſted, as alſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:115072:59"/>to be <hi>executed</hi> againſt them, when as they moleſt other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All covenants, and agreements made with them by our <hi>Governours;</hi> to be confirmed, publickly under hands, and <hi>Seals</hi> as mutually bnd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and obliging our Magiſtrates, to afford them <hi>juſt</hi> and honorable protection, and ſecurity for Lives and Eſtates, and they to render all <hi>Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Tribute,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome;</hi> to them for the ſame, that ſo <hi>we</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> may lead a <hi>quiet, ſober,</hi> and <hi>godly</hi> life; as being all children of the <hi>ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>Heirs</hi> of the ſame promiſe, and all hoping for the <hi>ſame</hi> Crown of Righteouſneſs, Immortality, and Glory: many others might have been added, but 'tis preſumption and unmanners, to give preſcription to our betters; and therefore we <hi>quietly</hi> and conſcienciouſly ſubmit, to their judgments and concluſions;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115072:59"/>praying heartily to God to give them the Spirit of <hi>wiſedom,</hi> and <hi>counſel,</hi> and <hi>valour,</hi> and the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord; that they may know <hi>how to go in and out,</hi> before this <hi>great</hi> people of the Lord their God; and the bleſſings of God be upon all their <hi>counſels</hi> and <hi>actions,</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>cauſe</hi> of God, in theſe and other Nations. Amen:</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
